<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tragicall history of the life and death of Doctor Faustus. Written by Ch. Marklin</title>
            <title>Doctor Faustus</title>
            <author>Marlowe, Christopher, 1564-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07013</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856262</idno>
  <idno type="VID">21791</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240884184</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 17432</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S121073</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99856262e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 815:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tragicall history of the life and death of Doctor Faustus. Written by Ch. Marklin</title>
                  <title>Doctor Faustus</title>
                  <author>Marlowe, Christopher, 1564-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Wright, and are to be sold at his shop without Newgate, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ch. Marklin = Christopher Marlowe.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ (-H4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The tragicall historie of Doctor Faustus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21791:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21791:1"/>
            <p>The Tragicall History of the Life and Death of <hi>Doctor Faustus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVritten by <hi>Ch. Marklin.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop without Newgate, at the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21791:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21791:2"/>
            <head>THE TRAGEDIE OF Doctor Faustus.</head>
            <stage>Enter Chorus.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>NOt marching in the fields of <hi>Thrasimen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi>Mars</hi> did mate the warlicke <hi>Carthagens,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor sporting in the dalliance of loue</l>
               <l>In Courts of Kings, where state is ouer-turn'd</l>
               <l>Nor in the pompe of proud audacious déeds,</l>
               <l>Intends our Muse to vaunt his heauenly verse</l>
               <l>Onely this, Gentles: we must now performe</l>
               <l>The forme of <hi>Faustus</hi> fortunes, good or bad,</l>
               <l>And now to patient iudgements we appeale,</l>
               <l>And speake for <hi>Faustus</hi> in his infancie.</l>
               <l>Now is he borne, of parents base of stocke,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Germany,</hi> within a Towne cal'd <hi>Rhodes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At riper yeares to <hi>Wittenberg</hi> he went,</l>
               <l>Whereas his kinsmen chiefly brought him vp;</l>
               <l>So much he profits in Diuinitie,</l>
               <l>That shortly he was grac'd with Doctors name,</l>
               <l>Excelling all, and swéetly can dispute</l>
               <l>In th'heauenly matters of Theologie,</l>
               <l>Till swolne with cunning, of a selfe conceit,</l>
               <l>His waxen wings did mount aboue his reach,</l>
               <l>And melting, heauens conspir'd his ouer-throw:</l>
               <l>For falling to a diuellishex ercise,</l>
               <l>And glutted now with learnings golden gifts,</l>
               <l>He surfets vpon cursed Necromancie:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:3"/>
               <l> Nothing so swéet as Magicke is to him;</l>
               <l>Which he preferres before his chiefest blisse,</l>
               <l>And this the man that in his study sits.</l>
               <stage>Faustus in his study.</stage>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Settle thy studies <hi>Faustus,</hi> and begin</l>
                  <l>To sound the depth of that thou wilt professe,</l>
                  <l>Hauing commenc'd, be a Diuine in shew,</l>
                  <l>Yet leuell at the end of euery Art,</l>
                  <l>And liue and die in <hi>Aristotles</hi> workes.</l>
                  <l>Swéet <hi>Analitikes,</hi> tis thou hast rauisht me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bene differere est finis Logicis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is to dispute well Logickes chiefest end?</l>
                  <l>Affoords this Art no greater miracle?</l>
                  <l>Then read no more, thou hast attain'd that end:</l>
                  <l>A greater subiect fitteth <hi>Faustus</hi> wit:</l>
                  <l>Bid <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>onomy</hi> farewell; and <hi>Galen</hi> come:</l>
                  <l>Be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>sitian <hi>Faustus,</hi> heape vp gold,</l>
                  <l>And be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>niz'd for some wondrous cure:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Summum bonum, medicinae sanitas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The end of Physicke is our bodies health:</l>
                  <l>Why <hi>Faustus,</hi> hast thou not attain'd that end?</l>
                  <l>Are not thy bils hung vp as monuments,</l>
                  <l>Wherby whole Cities haue escap't the plague,</l>
                  <l>And thousand desperate maladies beene cur'd?</l>
                  <l>Yet art thou still but <hi>Faustus,</hi> and a man.</l>
                  <l>Coulost thou make men to liue eternally,</l>
                  <l>Or being dead, raise them to life againe,</l>
                  <l>Then this profession were to be estéem'd.</l>
                  <l>Physicke farewell: where is <hi>Iustinian?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si vna eademque res legatus duobus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alter rem, alter valorem rei, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A petty case of paltry Legacies,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exhereditari filium non potest pater, nisi—</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such is the subiect of the institute,</l>
                  <l>And vniuersall body of the law.</l>
                  <l>This study fits a Mercenarie drudge,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho aimes at nothing but externall trash,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>uile aad illiberall for mée.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:3"/>
                  <l> When all is done, <hi>Diuinitie</hi> is best:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ieromes</hi> Bible <hi>Faustus,</hi> view it well:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stipendium peccati, mors est: ha, stipendium, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The reward of sin is death? that's hard:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si peccasse, negamus, fallimur, &amp; nulla est in nobis veritas:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If we say that we haue no sinne</l>
                  <l>We deceiue our selues, and there is no truth in vs.</l>
                  <l>Why then belike we must sinne,</l>
                  <l>And so consequently die,</l>
                  <l>I, we must die, an euerlasting death.</l>
                  <l>What doctrine call you this? <hi>Che sera, sera:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What will be, shall be; <hi>Diuinitie</hi> adeiw.</l>
                  <l>These Metaphisicks of Magitians,</l>
                  <l>And Negromantick bookes are heauenly,</l>
                  <l>Lines, Circles, Letters, Characters:</l>
                  <l>I these are those that <hi>Faustus</hi> most desires.</l>
                  <l>O what a world of profite and delight,</l>
                  <l>Of power, of honour, and omnipotence,</l>
                  <l>Is promised to the Studious Artizan?</l>
                  <l>All things that moue betweene the quiet Poles</l>
                  <l>Shall be at my command: Emperors and Kings,</l>
                  <l>Are but obey'd in their seuerall Prouinces:</l>
                  <l>But his dominion that exceeds in this,</l>
                  <l>Stretcheth as farre as doth the mind of man:</l>
                  <l>A sound Magitian is a Demi-god,</l>
                  <l>Heretire my braines to get a Deity.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Wagner.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wagner,</hi> commend me to my deerest friends,</l>
                  <l>The Germane <hi>Valdes</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Request them earnestly to visit me.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>I will sir.</p>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Their conference will be a greater helpe to me,</l>
                  <l>Then all my labours, plod I ne're so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>st.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter the Angell and Spirit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good A.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O <hi>Faustus,</hi> lay that damned booke aside,</l>
                  <l>And gaze not on it least it tempt thy soule,</l>
                  <l>And heape Gods heauy wrath vpon thy head.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:4"/>
                  <l> Reade, reade the Scriptures: that is blasphemy.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad A.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go forward <hi>Faustus</hi> in that famous Art</l>
                  <l>Wherein all natures treasure is contain'd:</l>
                  <l>Be thou on earth as <hi>loue</hi> is in the skye,</l>
                  <l>Lord and Commander of these elements:</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exeunt An.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How am I glutted with conceipt of this?</l>
                  <l>Shall I make spirits fetch me what I please?</l>
                  <l>Resolue me of all ambiguities?</l>
                  <l>Performe what desperate enterprise I will?</l>
                  <l>I'le haue them flie to <hi>Indian</hi> for gold;</l>
                  <l>Ransacke the Ocean for Orient Pearle,</l>
                  <l>And search all corners of the new-found-world</l>
                  <l>For pleasant fruites, and Princely delicates.</l>
                  <l>I'le haue them read me strange Philosophy,</l>
                  <l>And tell the secrets of all forraine Kings:</l>
                  <l>I'le haue them wall all <hi>Germany</hi> with Brasse,</l>
                  <l>And make swift <hi>Rhine,</hi> circle faire <hi>Wittenberge:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'le haue them fill the publique Schooles with skill,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith the Students shall be brauely clad.</l>
                  <l>I'le leauy souldiers with the coyne they bring,</l>
                  <l>And chase the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> from our Land,</l>
                  <l>And raigns sole King of all the Prouinces.</l>
                  <l>Yea stranger engines for the brunt of warre.</l>
                  <l>Then was the fiery keele at <hi>Anwerpe</hi> bridge,</l>
                  <l>I'le make my seruile spirits to inuent.</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Germane Valdes</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And make me blest with your sage conference.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Valdes and Cornelius.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valdes,</hi> sweets <hi>Valdes</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Know that your words haue won me at the last.</l>
                  <l>To practise Magicke and concealed Arts.</l>
                  <l>Philosophy is odious and obscure:</l>
                  <l>Both Law and Physicke are for petty wits,</l>
                  <l>'Tis magick, magick, that hath rauisht me.</l>
                  <l>Then gentle friends aid me in this attempt,</l>
                  <l>And I, that haue with subtle Sillogismes</l>
                  <l>Grauel'd the Pastors of the <hi>Germane</hi> Church,</l>
                  <l>And made the flowring pride of <hi>Wittenberg</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>worne to my Problemes, as th'infernall spirits</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:4"/>
                  <l> On sweet <hi>Musaeus</hi> when he came to hell,</l>
                  <l>Will be as cunning as <hi>Agrippa</hi> was,</l>
                  <l>Whose shadow made all <hi>Europe</hi> honour him.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Val.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus,</hi> these bookes, thy wit, and our experience,</l>
                  <l>shall make all Nations to Canonize vs,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Indian Moores,</hi> obey their <hi>Spanish</hi> Lords:</l>
                  <l>So shall the spirits of euery element,</l>
                  <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alwaies seruiceable to vs three:</l>
                  <l>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Lyons shall they guard vs when we please,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Almaine</hi> Rutters with their horsemens staues,</l>
                  <l>Or Lopland Giants trotting by our sides,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes like women or vnwedded Maides:</l>
                  <l>Shadowing more beauty in their Airie browes,</l>
                  <l>Then has the white breasts of the Queene of loue.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Venice</hi> shall they drag huge <hi>Argosies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And from <hi>America</hi> the Golden Fleece,</l>
                  <l>That yearely stuff'd old <hi>Phillips</hi> treasury,</l>
                  <l>If learned <hi>Faustus</hi> will be resolute.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valdes,</hi> as resolute am I in this,</l>
                  <l>As thou to liue, therefore obiect it not.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Corn.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>The miracles that magick will performe,</l>
                  <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> make thee vow to study nothing else.</l>
                  <l>He that is grounded in Astrology,</l>
                  <l>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ht with tongues, well seene in Minerals,</l>
                  <l>Hath all the Principles Magick doth require:</l>
                  <l>Then doubt not <hi>Faustus</hi> but to be renowm'd,</l>
                  <l>And more frequented for this mysterie,</l>
                  <l>Then heeretofore the <hi>Delphian</hi> Oracle.</l>
                  <l>The spirits tell me they can dry the sea,</l>
                  <l>And fetch the treasure of all forraine wrackes:</l>
                  <l>Yea all the wealth that our fore-fathers hid,</l>
                  <l>Within the massy entrailes of the earth:</l>
                  <l>Then tell me <hi>Faustus</hi> what shall we three want?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nothing <hi>Cornelius;</hi> O this cheeres my soule:</l>
                  <l>Come, shew me some demonstrations Magicall,</l>
                  <l>That I may coniure in some bushy Groue,</l>
                  <l>And haue these ioies in full possession.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Val.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then hast thee to some solitary Groue,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:5"/>
                  <l> And beare wise <hi>Bacons,</hi> and <hi>Albanus</hi> workes,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Hebrew</hi> Psalter, and new Testament;</l>
                  <l>And whatsoeuer else is requisite,</l>
                  <l>We will informe thee e're our conference cease.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valdes,</hi> first let him know the words of Art,</l>
                  <l>And then all other ceremonies learn'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus</hi> may try his cunning by himselfe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Val.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>First I'le instruct thee in the rudiments,</l>
                  <l>And then wilt thou be perfecter then I.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then come and dine with me, and after meate</l>
                  <l>We'le canuase euery quidditie thereof:</l>
                  <l>For e're I sleep, I'le try what I can do:</l>
                  <l>This night I'le coniure tho I die therefore.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exeunt om.</stage>
               <stage>Enter two Schollers.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I wonder what's become of <hi>Faustus</hi> that was wont</l>
                  <l>To make our schooles ring, with <hi>sic probo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter Wag.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>That shall we presently know, here comes his boy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>How now sirra, where's thy Maister?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>God in heauen knowes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Why dost not thou know then!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I know, but that followes not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Go to sirra, leaue your iesting, &amp; tell vs where he is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>That followes not by force of argument, which you, being <hi>Licentiats,</hi> should stand vpon, therefore acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your errour, and be attentiue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Then you will not tell vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>You are deceiu'd, for I will tell you: yet if you were not dunces, you would neuer aske me such a question: For is he not <hi>Corpus naturale?</hi> and is not that <hi>Mobile?</hi> Then wherefore should you aske me such a question? But that I am by nature flegmatique, slow to wrath, &amp; prone to letcherie (to loue I would say) it were not for you to come within for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie foot of the place of execution, although I do not doubt but to see you both hangd'd the next Sessions. Thus hauing tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpht ouer you, I will set my countenance like a Precisian, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> begin to speake thus: Truely my deere brethren, my M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.
<pb facs="tcp:21791:5"/> is with in at dinner, with <hi>Valdes</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi> as this wine, if it could speake, would informe your Worships: and so the Lord blesse you, preserue you, and keepe you, my deere brethren.</p>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O <hi>Faustus,</hi> then I feare y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which I haue long suspected:</l>
                  <l>That thou art falne into that damned Art</l>
                  <l>For which they two are infamous through the world.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Were he a stranger, not allyed to me,</l>
                  <l>The danger of his soule would make me mourne:</l>
                  <l>But come, let vs go, and informe the <hi>Rector:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It may be his graue counsell may reclaime him.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I feare me, nothing will reclaime him now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Sch.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Yet let vs see what we can do.</p>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Thunder. <hi>Enter Lucifer and</hi>
                  </hi> 4 <hi>deuils, <hi>Faustus</hi> to them with this speech.</hi>
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now that the gloomy shadow of the night,</l>
                  <l>Longing to view <hi>Orions</hi> drisling looke,</l>
                  <l>Leapes from th'Antarticke world vnto the skie,</l>
                  <l>And dyms the <hi>Welkin,</hi> with her pitchy breathe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus,</hi> begin thine Incantations,</l>
                  <l>And try if deuils will obey thy Hest,</l>
                  <l>Seeing thou hast pray'd and sacrific'd to them.</l>
                  <l>Within this circle is <hi>Iehoua's</hi> Name,</l>
                  <l>Forward, and backward, <hi>Anagramatis'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Th'abreuiated names of holy Saints,</l>
                  <l>Figures of euery adiunct to the heauens,</l>
                  <l>And Characters of Signes, and euening Starres,</l>
                  <l>By which the spirits are inforc'd to rise:</l>
                  <l>Then feare not <hi>Faustus</hi> to be resolute</l>
                  <l>And try the vtmost Magicke can performe.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thunder, <hi>Sint mihi Dij Acherontis propitij, valeat numen tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex Iehouae, ignei Aerij, Aquatani spiritus saluete: Orientis Princeps Belzebub, inferni ardentis monarcha &amp; demigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, propitiamus vos, vt appareat, &amp; surgat Mephostophilis Dragon, quod tumeraris; per Iehouam, gehennan, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secratam</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:6"/>
                  <hi>aquam, quam nunc spargo; signum{que} crucis quod nunc facio; &amp; per vota nostra ipse nunc surgat nobis dicatis Mephostophilis.</hi>
               </p>
               <stage>Enter a Deuill.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>I charge thee to returne, and change thy shape,</l>
                  <l>Thou art too vgly to attend on me:</l>
                  <l>Go and returne an old <hi>Franciscan</hi> Frier,</l>
                  <l>That holy shape becomes a deuill best.</l>
                  <stage>Exit deuill.</stage>
                  <l>I see there's vertue in my heauenly words.</l>
                  <l>Who would not be proficient in this Art?</l>
                  <l>How pliant is this <hi>Mephostophilis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Full of obedience and humility,</l>
                  <l>Such is the force of Magicke, and my spels.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter Mephostophilis.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Now <hi>Faustus</hi> what wouldst thou haue me do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I charge thee waite vpon me whilst I liue</l>
                  <l>To do what euer <hi>Faustus</hi> shall command:</l>
                  <l>Be it to make the Moone drop from her Sphere,</l>
                  <l>Or the Ocean to ouerwhelme the world.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I am a seruant to great <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And may not follow thee without his leaue;</l>
                  <l>No more then he commands, must we performe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Did not he charge thee to appeare to me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>No, I came now hether of mine owne accdrd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Did not my coniuring raise thee? speake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>That was the cause, but yet <hi>per accident:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For when we heare one racke the name of God,</l>
                  <l>Abiure the Scriptures, and his Sauiour Christ:</l>
                  <l>We flye in hope to get his glorious soule;</l>
                  <l>Nor will we come vnlesse he vse such meanes,</l>
                  <l>Whereby he is in danger to be damn'd:</l>
                  <l>Therefore the shortest cut for coniuring</l>
                  <l>Is stoutly to abiure all godlinesse,</l>
                  <l>And pray deuoutely to the Prince of hell.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So <hi>Faustus</hi> hath already done, and holds this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> is no chiefe but onely <hi>Beelzebub:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:6"/>
                  <l> To whom <hi>Faustus</hi> doth dedicate himselfe.</l>
                  <l>This word Damnation, terrifies not me,</l>
                  <l>For I confound hell in <hi>Elizium:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Ghost be with the old Phylosophers.</l>
                  <l>But leauing these vaine trifles of mens soules,</l>
                  <l>Tell me, what is that <hi>Lucifer,</hi> thy Lord?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Arch-regent and Commander of all Spirits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Was not that <hi>Lucifer</hi> an Angell once?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Yes <hi>Faustus,</hi> and most deerely lou'd of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>How comes it then that he is Prince of Deuils?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O: by aspiring pride and insolence,</l>
                  <l>For which God threw him from the face of heauen.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>And what are you that liue with Lucifer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnhappy spirits that liue with Lucifer,</l>
                  <l>Conspir'd against our God with Lucifer,</l>
                  <l>And are for euer damn'd with Lucifer.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Where are you damn'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>In hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>How comes it then that thou art out of hell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why this is hell: nor am I out of it.</l>
                  <l>Think'st thou that I that saw the face of God,</l>
                  <l>And tasted the eternall Ioyes of heauen,</l>
                  <l>Am not tormented with ten thousand hels,</l>
                  <l>In being depriu'd of euerlasting blisse?</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Faustus</hi> leaue these friuolous demandes,</l>
                  <l>Which strikes a terror to my fainting soule.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What is great <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> so passionate</l>
                  <l>For being depriued of the Ioyes of heauen?</l>
                  <l>Learne thou of <hi>Faustus</hi> manly fortitude,</l>
                  <l>And scorne those Ioyes thou neuer shalt possesse.</l>
                  <l>Go beare these tydings to great Lucifer,</l>
                  <l>Seeing <hi>Faustus</hi> hath incur'd eternall death,</l>
                  <l>By desperate thoughts against <hi>Ioues</hi> Deity:</l>
                  <l>Say he surrenders vp to him his soule,</l>
                  <l>So he will spare him foure and twenty yeares,</l>
                  <l>Letting him liue in all voluptuousnesse,</l>
                  <l>Hauing thee euer to attend on me,</l>
                  <l>To giue me whatsoeuer I shall aske;</l>
                  <l>To tell me whatsoeuer I demand:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:7"/>
                  <l> To slay mine enemies, and to aid my friends,</l>
                  <l>And alwaies be obedient to my will.</l>
                  <l>Go, and returne to mighty <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And meet me in my Study, at Midnight,</l>
                  <l>And then resolue me of thy Maisters mind.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>I will <hi>Faustus.</hi>
               </p>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had I as many soules, as there be Starres,</l>
                  <l>I'de giue them all for <hi>Mephostophilis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By him, I'le be great Emperour of the world,</l>
                  <l>And make a bridge, through the mouing Aire,</l>
                  <l>To passe the Ocean: with a band of men</l>
                  <l>I'le ioyne the Hils that bind the <hi>Affrick</hi> shore,</l>
                  <l>And make that Country, continent to <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And both contributary to my Crowne.</l>
                  <l>The Emperour shall not liue, but by my leaue,</l>
                  <l>Nor any Potentate of <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now that I haue obtain'd what I desir'd</l>
                  <l>I'le liue in speculation of this Art</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> returne againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Wagner and the Clowne.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Come hither sirra boy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
               <p>Boy? O disgrace to my person: Zounds boy in your face, you haue seene many boyes with beards I am sure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra, hast thou no commings In?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and goings out too, you may see sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Alas poore slaue, see how pouerty iests in his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, I know the Villaines out of seruice, and so hungry, that I know he would giue his soule to the deuill, for a shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Mutton, tho it were bloud raw.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
               <p>Not so neither; I had need to haue it well rosted, and good sauce to it, if I pay so deere, I can tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra, wilt thou be my man and waite on me? and I will make thee go, like <hi>Qui mihi discipulus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>What, in Verse?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>No slaue, in beaten silke, and staues-aker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ow.</speaker>
               <p>Staues-aker? that's good to kill Vermine: then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:21791:7"/> if I serue you, I shall be lousy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Why so thou shalt be, whether thou dost it or no: for sirra, if thou dost not presently bind thy selfe to me for seuen yeares, I'le turne all the lice about thee into Familiars, and make them tare thee in peeces.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Nay sir, you may saue your selfe a labour, for they are as familiar with me, as if they payd for their meate and drinke, I can tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Well sirra, leaue your iesting, and take these Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Yes marry sir, and I thanke you to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>So, now thou art to bee at an howres warning, whensoeuer, and wheresoeuer the deuill shall fetch thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Here, take your Guilders I'le none of 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Not I, thou art Prest, prepare thy selfe, for I will presently raise vp two deuils to carry thee away: <hi>Banio, Belcher.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Belcher?</hi> and <hi>Belcher</hi> come here, I'le belch him: I am not afraid of a deuill.</p>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> 2 <hi>deuils.</hi>
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>How now sir will you serue me now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>I good <hi>Wagner</hi> take away the deuill then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Spirits away; now sirra follow me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>I will sir; but hearke you Maister, will you teach me this coniuring Occupation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>I sirra, I'le teach thee to turne thy selfe to a Dog, or a Cat, or a Mouse, or a Rat, or any thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>A Dog, or a Cat, or a Mouse, or a Rat? O braue <hi>Wagner.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>Villaine, call me Maister <hi>Wagner,</hi> and see that you walke atttentiuely, and let your right eye be alwaies, <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trally</hi> fixt vpon my left heele, that thou maist, <hi>Quasi vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gias nostras insistere.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Well sir, I warrant you.</p>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Faustus in his Study.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Faustus,</hi> must thou needs be damn'd?</l>
                  <l>Canst thou not be sau'd?</l>
                  <l>What bootes it then to thinke on God or Heauen?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:8"/>
                  <l> Away with such vaine fancies, and despaire,</l>
                  <l>Despaire in <hi>GOD,</hi> and trust in <hi>Belzebub,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now go not backward <hi>Faustus,</hi> be resolute.</l>
                  <l>Why wauerst thou? O something soundeth in mine eare.</l>
                  <l>Abu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce this Magicke, turne to God againe.</l>
                  <l>Why he loues thee not: The God thou seru'st is thine owne appetite</l>
                  <l>Wherein is fixt the loue of <hi>Belzebub,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To him, I'le build an Altar and a Church,</l>
                  <l>And offer luke-warme bloud, of new borne babes.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter the two Angels.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euill An.</speaker>
               <p>Go forward <hi>Faustus</hi> in that famous Art.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good An.</speaker>
               <p>Sweete <hi>Faustus</hi> leaue that execrable Art.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Contrition, Prayer, Repentance? what of these?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good A.</speaker>
               <p>O they are meanes to bring thee vnto heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad A.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rather illusions, fruits of lunacy.</l>
                  <l>That make them foolish that do vse them most.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good A.</speaker>
               <p>Swéet <hi>Faustus</hi> think of heauen, &amp; heauenly things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad A.</speaker>
               <p>No <hi>Faustus</hi> thinke of honour and of wealth.</p>
               <stage>Ex. An.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wealth? Why the Signory of <hi>Embden</hi> shall be mine:</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> shall stand by me,</l>
                  <l>What power can hurt me? <hi>Faustus</hi> thou art safe.</l>
                  <l>Cast no more doubts; <hi>Mepho:</hi> come</l>
                  <l>And bring glad tydings from great <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ist not midnight? come <hi>Mephostophilis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Veni veni Mephostophile.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Mephosto.</stage>
                  <l>Now tell me what saith <hi>Lucifer</hi> thy Lord.</l>
                  <l>That I shall waite on <hi>Faustus</hi> whilst he liues,</l>
                  <l>So he will buy my seruice with his soule.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Already <hi>Faustus</hi> hath hazarded that for thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now thou must bequeath it solemnly,</l>
                  <l>And wright a Deed of Gift with thine owne bloud;</l>
                  <l>For that security craues <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou deny it I must backe to hell.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stay <hi>Mephosto.</hi> and tell me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat good will my soule do thy Lord?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </speaker>
               <p>Enlarge his Kingdome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:8"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Is that the reason why he tempts vs thus?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solamen miseris, socios habuisse doloris.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Why, haue you any paine that torture other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>As great as haue the humane soules of men.</l>
                  <l>But tell me <hi>Faustus,</hi> shall I haue thy soule?</l>
                  <l>And I will be thy slaue and waite on thee,</l>
                  <l>And giue thee more then thou hast wit to aske.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>Mephostophilis,</hi> I'le giue it him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then <hi>Faustus</hi> stab thy Arme couragiously,</l>
                  <l>And bind thy soule, that at some certaine day</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Lucifer</hi> may claime it as his owne,</l>
                  <l>And then be thou as great as <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe <hi>Mephosto:</hi> for loue of thee <hi>Faustus</hi> hath cut his arme,</l>
                  <l>And with his prope rbloud assures his soule to be great <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Chiefe Lord and Regent of perpetuall night.</l>
                  <l>Veiw here this bloud that trickles from mine arme,</l>
                  <l>And let it be propitious for my wish.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Faustus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Write it in manner of a Deed of Gift.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I so I do; but <hi>Mephostophilis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My bloud congeales, and I can write no more.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>I'le fetch thee fire to dissolue it streight.</p>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What might the staying of my bloud portend?</l>
                  <l>Is it vnwilling I should write this byll?</l>
                  <l>Why streames it not, that I may write a fresh?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus</hi> giues to thee his soule: O there it staid.</l>
                  <l>Why shouldst thou not? is not thy soule thine owne?</l>
                  <l>Then write againe: <hi>Faustus</hi> giues to thee his soule.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter Mephostoph: with the Chafer of Fire.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>See <hi>Faustus</hi> here is fire, set it on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So, now the bloud begins to cleere againe:</l>
                  <l>Now will I make an end immediately.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>What will not I do to obtaine his soule?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Consummatum est:</hi> this byll is ended,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Faustus</hi> hath bequeath'd his soule to <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But what is this Inscription on mine Arme?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:9"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Homo fuge,</hi> whether should I flye?</l>
                  <l>If vnto heauen, hee'le throw me downe to hell.</l>
                  <l>My sences are deceiu'd, here's nothing writ:</l>
                  <l>O yes, I see it plaine, euen heere is writ</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Homo fuge,</hi> yet shall not <hi>Faustus</hi> flye.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>I'le fetch him somewhat to delight his minde.</p>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Deuils, giuing Crownes and rich apparell to Faustus: they dance, and then depart. Enter Mephostophilis.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>What meanes this shew? speake <hi>Mephostophilis.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nothing <hi>Faustus</hi> but to delight thy mind,</l>
                  <l>And let thee see what Magicke can performe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>But may I raise such spirits when I please?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>Faustus,</hi> and do greater things then these.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> receiue this scrole,</l>
                  <l>A Deed of Gift, of body and of soule:</l>
                  <l>But yet conditionally, that thou performe</l>
                  <l>All Couenants, and Articles, betweene vs both.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus,</hi> I sweare by <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To effect all promises betweene vs both.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then heare me read it <hi>Mephostophilis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On these conditions following.</l>
               </lg>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <item>First, that Faustus may be a spirit in forme and substance.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, that Mephostophilis shall be his seruant, and be by him commanded.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, that Mephostophilis shall doe for him, and bring him whatsoeuer.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, that he shall be in his chamber or house inuisible.</item>
                     <item>Lastly, that hee shall appeare to the said Iohn Faustus, at all times, in what shape and forme soeuer he please.</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Iohn Faustus of Wittenberg, Doctor, by these presents, doe giue both body and soule to Lucifer, Prince of rhe East, and his Minister Mephastophilis, and furthermore grant vnto them that foure and twentie yeares being expired, and these Articles aboue written being inviolate, full power to fetch or carry the</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:9"/>
                  <hi>said Iohn Faustus, body and soule, flesh, bloud, into their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation wheresoeuer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By me <hi>Iohn Faustus.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Speake <hi>Faustus,</hi> do you deliuer this as your Déed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I take it, and the deuill giue thee good of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>So, now <hi>Faustus</hi> aske me what thou wilt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>First, I will question thee about hell:</l>
                  <l>Tell me, where is the place that men call Hell?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Vnder the heauens.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I, so are all things else; but whereabouts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Within the bowels of these Elements,</l>
                  <l>Where we are tortur'd, and remaine for euer.</l>
                  <l>Hell hath no limits, nor is circumscrib'd,</l>
                  <l>In one selfe place: but where we are is hell,</l>
                  <l>And where hell is there must we euer be.</l>
                  <l>And to be short, when all the world dissolues,</l>
                  <l>And euery creature shall be purifi'd,</l>
                  <l>All places shall be hell that is not heauen.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke Hel's a fable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>I, thinke so still, till experience change thy mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Why, dost thou think that <hi>Faustus</hi> shall be damn'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, of necessity, for here's the scrowle</l>
                  <l>In which thou hast giuen thy soule to <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, and body too, but what of that:</l>
                  <l>Think'st thou that <hi>Faustus,</hi> is so fond to imagine,</l>
                  <l>That after this life there is any paine?</l>
                  <l>No, these are trifles, and meere old wiues Tales.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I am an instance to proue the contrary:</l>
                  <l>For I tell thee I am damn'd, and now in hell.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, and this be hell, I'le willingly be damn'd.</l>
                  <l>What sléeping, eating, walking and disputing?</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But leauing this, let me haue a wife, the fairest Maid in <hi>Germany,</hi> for I am wanton and lasciuious, and cannot liue without a wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Well <hi>Faustus,</hi> thou shalt haue a wife.</p>
               <stage>He fetches in a woman deuill.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>What sight is this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:10"/>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Now <hi>Faustus</hi> wilt thou haue a wife?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Here's a hot whore indéed; no, I'le no wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Marriage is but a ceremoniall toy,</l>
                  <l>And if thou louest me thinke no more of it,</l>
                  <l>I'le cull thee out the fairest Curtezans,</l>
                  <l>And bring them euery morning to thy bed:</l>
                  <l>She whom thine eye shall like, thy heart shall haue,</l>
                  <l>Were she as chaste as was <hi>Penelope;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As wise as <hi>Saba,</hi> or as beautifull</l>
                  <l>As was bright <hi>Lucifer</hi> before his fall.</l>
                  <l>Here, take this booke, and peruse it well:</l>
                  <l>The Iterating of these lines brings gold;</l>
                  <l>The framing of this circle on the ground</l>
                  <l>Brings Thunder, Whirle-winds, Storme and Lightning:</l>
                  <l>Pronounce this thrice deuoutly to thy selfe,</l>
                  <l>And men in harnesse shall appeare to thee,</l>
                  <l>Ready to execute what thou commandst.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thankes <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> for this sweete booke.</l>
                  <l>This will I keepe, as chary as my life.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Wagner solus.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Learned <hi>Faustus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To know the secrets of Astronomy</l>
                  <l>Grauen in the booke of <hi>Ioues</hi> high firmament,</l>
                  <l>Did mount himselfe to scale <hi>Olympus</hi> top,</l>
                  <l>Being seated in a chariot burning bright,</l>
                  <l>Drawne by the strength of yoaky Dragons necks,</l>
                  <l>He now is gone to proue Cosmography,</l>
                  <l>And as I gesse will first arriue at <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To see the Pope and manner of his Court;</l>
                  <l>And take some part of holy <hi>Peters</hi> feast,</l>
                  <l>That to this day is highly solemnized.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Wagner.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Faustus in his Study, and Mephostophilis.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>When I behold the heauens then I repent</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> curse thee wicked <hi>Mephostophilis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:10"/>
                  <l> Because thou hast depriu'd me of those Ioyes.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Twas thine own seeking <hi>Faustus,</hi> thanke thy selfe.</l>
                  <l>But think'st thou heauen is such a glorious thing?</l>
                  <l>I tell thee <hi>Faustus</hi> it is not halfe so faire</l>
                  <l>As thou, or any man that breathe on earth.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>How prou'st thou that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>'Twas made for man; then he's more excellent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If Heauen was made for man, 'twas made for me:</l>
                  <l>I will renounce this Magicke and repent.</l>
                  <stage>Enter the two Angels.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faustus</hi> repent, yet God will pitty thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad A.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art a spirit, God cannot pity thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who buzzeth in mine eares I am a spirit?</l>
                  <l>Be I a deuill yet God may pitty me.</l>
                  <l>Yea, God will pitty me if I repent.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euill An.</speaker>
               <p>I, but <hi>Faustus</hi> neuer shall repent.</p>
               <stage>Exit Angels.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My heart is hardned, I cannot repent:</l>
                  <l>Scarce can I name saluation, faith, or heauen.</l>
                  <l>Swords, poyson, halters, and inuenomb'd stéele,</l>
                  <l>Are laid before me to dispatch my selfe:</l>
                  <l>And long e're this, I should haue done the deed,</l>
                  <l>Had not sweete pleasure conquer'd deepe despaire.</l>
                  <l>Haue not I made blind <hi>Homer</hi> sing to me</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Alexanders</hi> loue, and <hi>Oenons</hi> death?</l>
                  <l>And hath not he that built the walles of <hi>Thebes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With rauishing sound of his melodious Harpe,</l>
                  <l>Made musicke with my <hi>Mephostophilis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Why should I die then, or basely despaire?</l>
                  <l>I am resolu'd, <hi>Faustus</hi> shall not repent.</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> let vs dispute againe,</l>
                  <l>And reason of diuine Astrology.</l>
                  <l>Speake, are there many Spheares aboue the Moone?</l>
                  <l>Are all Celestiall bodies but one Globe,</l>
                  <l>As is the substance of this centricke earth?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:11"/>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>As are the elements, such are the heauens,</l>
                  <l>Euen from the Moone vnto the Emperiall Orbe,</l>
                  <l>Mutually folded in each others Spheares,</l>
                  <l>And iontly moue vpon one Axle-trée,</l>
                  <l>Who etern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, is tearmed the worlds wide Pole.</l>
                  <l>Nor are the names of <hi>Saturne, Mars,</hi> or <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fain'd, but are euening Starres.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>But haue they all one motion, both <hi>situ &amp; tempore?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>All moue from East to West, in foure and twenty houres, vpon the poles of the world, but differ in their motions vpon the poles of the Zodiacke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>These slender questions <hi>Wagner</hi> can decide:</l>
                  <l>Hath <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> no greater skill?</l>
                  <l>Who knowes not the double motion of the Planets?</l>
                  <l>That the first is finisht in a naturall day?</l>
                  <l>The second thus, <hi>Saturne</hi> in 30 yeares;</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter</hi> in 12, <hi>Mars</hi> in 4, the <hi>Sun, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> in a yeare; the Moone in twenty eight daies.</p>
               <p>These are fresh mens questions: But tell me, hath euery Spheare a Dominion, or <hi>Intelligentia.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>How many Heauens, or Spheares, are there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Nine, the seuen Planets, the Firmament, and the Emperiall heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>But is there not <hi>Coelum igneum, &amp; Christalinum?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>No <hi>Faustus</hi> they be but Fables.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Resolue me then in this one question:</p>
               <p>Why are not Coniunctions, Oppositions, Aspects, Eclipses, all at one time, but in some years we haue more, in some lesse?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Per inae qualem motum, respectu totius.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I am answer'd: now tell me who made the world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>I will not</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Sweet <hi>Mephostophilis</hi> tell me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Moue me not <hi>Faustus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Villaine, haue not I bound thee to tell me any thing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, that is not against our Kingdome.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his is: Thou art damn'd, think thou of hell.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Thinke <hi>Faustus</hi> vpon God, that made she world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eph.</speaker>
               <p>Remember this,—</p>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:11"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, go accursed spirit to vgly hell:</l>
                  <l>'Tis thou hast damn'd distressed <hi>Faustus</hi> soule. Ist not too late?</l>
                  <stage>Enter the two Angels.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad.</speaker>
               <p>Too late.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good.</speaker>
               <p>Neuer too late, if <hi>Faustus</hi> will repent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad.</speaker>
               <p>If thou repent, deuils will teare thee in peeces.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good.</speaker>
               <p>Repent and they shall neuer raise thy skin.</p>
               <stage>Ex. A.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Christ my Sauiour, my Sauiour,</l>
                  <l>Helpe to saue distressed <hi>Faustus</hi> soule.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Lucifer, Belzebub, and Mephostophilis.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucif.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Christ cannot saue thy soule, for he is iust,</l>
                  <l>There's none but I haue interest in the same.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>O what art thou that look'st so terribly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucif.</speaker>
               <p>I am <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and this is my companion Prince in hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>O <hi>Faustus</hi> they are come to fetch thy soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belz.</speaker>
               <p>We are come to tell thee thou dost iniure vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucif.</speaker>
               <p>Thou calst on Christ contrary to thy promise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bels.</speaker>
               <p>Thou should'st not thinke on God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucif.</speaker>
               <p>Thinke on the deuill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belz.</speaker>
               <p>And his dam to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor will <hi>Faustus</hi> henceforth: pardon him for this,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Faustus</hi> vowes neuer to looke to heauen.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucif.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So shalt thou shew thy selfe an obedient seruant,</l>
                  <l>And we will highly gratify thee for it.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belz.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faustus</hi> we are come from hell in person to shew thee some pastime: fit downe and thou shalt behold the seuen deadly sinnes appeare to thee in their owne proper shapes and likenesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>That sight will be as pleasant to me, as Paradise was to <hi>Adam</hi> the first day of his creation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucif.</speaker>
               <p>Talke not of Paradice or Creation, but marke the shew, go <hi>Mephostoph.</hi> fetch them in.</p>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter the</hi> 7 <hi>deadly sinnes.</hi>
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Belz.</speaker>
               <p>Now <hi>Faustus,</hi> question them of their names and dispositions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:12"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>That shall I soone: What art thou the first?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pride.</speaker>
               <p>I am Pride; I disdaine to haue any parents: I am like to <hi>Ouids</hi> Flea, I can creepe into euery corner of a Wench: Sometimes, like a Perriwig, I fit vpon her Brow: next, like a Necke-lace I hang about her Necke: Then, like a Fan of Feathers, I kisse her; And then tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my selfe to a wrought Smocke do what I list. But fye, what a smell is heere? I'le not speake a word more for a Kings ransome, vnlesse the ground be perfum'd, and couer'd with cloth of Arras.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art a proud knaue indeed: What art thou the second?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Couet.</speaker>
               <p>I am <hi>Couetousnesse:</hi> begotten of an old Churle in a leather bag; and might I now obtaine my wish, this house you and all, should turne to Gold, that I might locke you safe into my Chest: O my sweete Gold!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>And what art thou the third?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Enuy.</speaker>
               <p>I am <hi>Enuy,</hi> begotten of a Chimney-sweeper, and an Oyster-wife: I cannot read, and therefore wish all books burn'd. I am leane with seeing others eate: O that there would come a famine ouer all the world, that all might die, and I liue alone, then thou should'st see how fat I'de be. But must thou sit, and I stand? come downe with a vengeance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Out enuious wretch: But what art thou the fourth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wrath.</speaker>
               <p>I am <hi>Wrath;</hi> I had neither father nor mother, I leapt out of a Lyons mouth when I was scarce an houre old, and euer since haue run vp and downe the world with these case of Rapiers, wounding my selfe when I could get none to fight withall: I was borne in hell, and look to it, for some of you shall be my father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>And what art thou the fift?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glut.</speaker>
               <p>I am <hi>Gluttony;</hi> my parents are all dead, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill a peny they haue left me, but a small pention, and that buyes me thirty meales a day, and ten Beauers: a small trifle to suffice nature. I come of a Royall Pedigree, my father was a Gammon of Bacon, and my mother was a Hogs-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Claret Wine. My godfathers were these: Peter-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>-herring, and Martin Martlemasse-béefe: But my god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother,
<pb facs="tcp:21791:12"/> O she was an ancient Gentlewoman, her name was Margery March-béere: Now <hi>Faustus</hi> thou hast heard all my progeny, wilt thou bid me to supper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Not I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>▪</speaker>
               <p>Then the deuill chooke thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Choke thy selfe Glutton: What art thou the sixt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sloth.</speaker>
               <p>Hey ho; I am <hi>Sloth:</hi> I was begotten on a sunny-bank: hey ho: I'le not speak a word more for a kings ransome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <p>And what are you Mistris Minkés, the seuenth &amp; last?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Letch.</speaker>
               <p>Who I I sir? I am one that loues an inch of raw Mutton, better then an ell of fryde Stockfish: and the first letter of my name begins with <hi>Letchery.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
               <p>Away to hell, away on piper.</p>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex. the</hi> 7 <hi>sinnes.</hi>
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>O how this sight doth delight my soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
               <p>But <hi>Faustus,</hi> in hell is all manner of delight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>O might I see hell, and returne againe safe, how happy were I then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faustus,</hi> thou shalt, at midnight I will send for thee; Meane while peruse this booke, and view it throughly, And thou shalt turne thy selfe into what shape thou wilt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thankes mighty <hi>Lucifer:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This will I keepe as chary as my life.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
               <p>Now <hi>Faustus</hi> farewell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Farewell great <hi>Lucifer:</hi> come <hi>Mephostophilis</hi>
               </p>
               <stage>Exeunt omnes, seuerall waies.</stage>
               <stage>Enter the Clowne.</stage>
               <p>What <hi>Dick,</hi> looke to the horses there till I come againe.</p>
               <p>I haue gotten one of Doctor <hi>Faustus</hi> coniuring bookes, and now we'le haue such knauery, as't passes.</p>
               <stage>Enter Dick.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>What <hi>Robin,</hi> you must come away &amp; walk the horses.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>I walke the horses, I scorn't 'faith, I haue other matters in hand, let the horses walk themselues and they will. <hi>A perse a, t. h. e the: o per se o deny orgon, gorgon:</hi> keepe further from me O thou illiterate, and vnlearned Hostler.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Snayles, what hast thou got there a book? why thou canst not tell ne're a word on't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:13"/>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>That thou shalt see presently: keep out of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, I say, least I send you into the Ostry with a vengeance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>That's like 'faith: you had best leaue your foolery, for an my Maister come, he'le coniure you 'faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>My Maister coniure me? I'le tell thee what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an my Maister come here, I'le clap as faire a paire of hornes on's head as e're thou sawest in thy life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Thou néedst not do that, for my Mistresse hath done it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>I, there be of vs here, that haue waded as deepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to matters, as other men, if they were disposed to talke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>A plague take you, I thought you did not sneak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vp and downe after her for nothing. But I prethee tell me, in good sadnesse <hi>Robin,</hi> is that a coniuring booke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>Do but speake what thou't haue me to do, and I'le do't: If thou't dance naked, put off thy cloathes, and I'le coniure thee about presently: Or if thou't go but to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne with me, I'le giue thee white wine, red wine, claret wine, Sacke, Muskadine, Malmesey and Whippincrust, hold belly hold, and wee'le not pay one peny for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>O braue, prethee let's to it presently, for I am as dry as a dog.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>Come then let's away.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter the Chorus.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>Learned <hi>Faustus</hi> to find the secrets of Astronomy,</l>
               <l>Grauen in the booke of <hi>Ioues</hi> high firmament,</l>
               <l>Did mount him vp to scale <hi>Olimpus</hi> top.</l>
               <l>Where sitting in a Chariot burning bright,</l>
               <l>Drawne by the strength of yoked Dragons neckes;</l>
               <l>He viewes the cloudes, the Planets, and the Starres,</l>
               <l>The Tropick, Zones, and quarters of the skye,</l>
               <l>From the bright circle of the horned Moone,</l>
               <l>Euen to the height of <hi>Primum Mobile:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And whirling round with this circumference,</l>
               <l>Within the concaue compasse of the Pole,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>om East to West his Dragons swiftly glide,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in eight daies did bring him home againe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:13"/>
               <l> Not long he stayed within his quiet house,</l>
               <l>To rest his bones after his weary toyle,</l>
               <l>But new exploits do hale him out agen,</l>
               <l>And mounted then vpon a Dragons backe,</l>
               <l>That w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th his wings did part the subtle aire:</l>
               <l>He now is gone to proue <hi>Cosmography,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That measures costs, and kingdomes of the earth:</l>
               <l>And as I guesse will first arriue at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To see the Pope and manner of his Court,</l>
               <l>And take some part of holy <hi>Peters</hi> feast,</l>
               <l>The which this day is highly solemnized.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Faustus and Mephostophilis.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hauing now my good <hi>Mephostophilis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Past with delight the stately Towne of <hi>Trier:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inuironed round with airy mountaine tops,</l>
                  <l>With wals of Flint, and deepe intrenched Lakes,</l>
                  <l>Not to be wonne by any conquering Prince.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Paris</hi> next, costing the Realme of <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We saw the Riuer <hi>Maine,</hi> fall into <hi>Rhines,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whose bankes are set with Groues of fruitfull Vines.</l>
                  <l>Then vp to <hi>Naples,</hi> rich <hi>Campania,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whose buildings faire, and gorgeous to the eye,</l>
                  <l>The streetes straight forth, and paued with finest bricke.</l>
                  <l>There saw we learned <hi>Maroes</hi> golden tombe:</l>
                  <l>The way he cut an English mile in length,</l>
                  <l>Through a rocke of stone in one nights space:</l>
                  <l>From thence to <hi>Venice, Padua,</hi> and the East,</l>
                  <l>In one of which a sumptuous Temple stands,</l>
                  <l>That threates the starres with her aspiring toy,</l>
                  <l>Whose frame is paued with sundry coloured stones,</l>
                  <l>And roof't aloft with curious worke in gold.</l>
                  <l>Thus hitherto hath <hi>Faustus</hi> spent his time.</l>
                  <l>But tell me now, what resting place is this?</l>
                  <l>Hast thou, as earst I did command,</l>
                  <l>Conducted me within the walles of <hi>Rome?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I haue my <hi>Faustus,</hi> and for proofe thereof,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:14"/>
                  <l> This is the goodly Palace of the Pope:</l>
                  <l>And cause we are no common guests,</l>
                  <l>I chuse his priuy chamber for our vse.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I hope his Holinesse will bid vs welcome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>All's one, for wee'l be bold with his Venso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>▪</l>
                  <l>But now my <hi>Faustus,</hi> that thou maist perceiue,</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Rome</hi> containes for to delight thine eyes.</l>
                  <l>Know that this City stands vpon seuen hils,</l>
                  <l>That vnderprop the ground-worke of the same:</l>
                  <l>Iust through the midst runnes flowing <hi>Tybers</hi> streame,</l>
                  <l>With winding bankes that cut it in two parts;</l>
                  <l>Ouer the which two stately Bridges leane,</l>
                  <l>That make safe passage, to each part of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vpon the Bridge, call'd <hi>Ponto Angelo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Erected is a Castle passing strong,</l>
                  <l>Where thou shalt see such store of Ordinance,</l>
                  <l>As that the double Cannons forg'd of brasse,</l>
                  <l>Do watch the number of the daies contain'd,</l>
                  <l>Within the compasse of one compleat yeare:</l>
                  <l>Beside the gates, and high Pyramydes,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> brought from <hi>Affrica.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now by the Kingdomes of Infernall Rule,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Stix,</hi> of <hi>Acheron,</hi> and the fiery Lake,</l>
                  <l>Of euer-burning <hi>Phlegeton,</hi> I sweare,</l>
                  <l>That I do long to see the Monuments</l>
                  <l>And situation of bright splendent <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Come therefore, let's away.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay stay my <hi>Faustus:</hi> I know you'd see the Pope</l>
                  <l>And take some part of holy <hi>Peters</hi> feast,</l>
                  <l>The which this day with high solemnity,</l>
                  <l>This day is held through <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In honour of the Popes triumphant victory.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sweete <hi>Mephosto.</hi> thou pleasest me</l>
                  <l>Whilst I am here on earth: Let me be cloyd</l>
                  <l>With all things that delight the heart of man.</l>
                  <l>My foure and twenty yeares of liberty</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>e spend in pleasure and in daliance,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>t <hi>Faustus</hi> name, whilst this bright frame doth stand,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:14"/>
                  <l> May be admired through the furthest Land.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis well said <hi>Faustus,</hi> come then stand by me</l>
                  <l>And thou shalt sée them come immediately.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay stay my gentle <hi>Mephostophilis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And grant me my request, and then I go.</l>
                  <l>Thou know'st within the compasse of eight daies,</l>
                  <l>We veiw'd the face of heauen, of earth and hell.</l>
                  <l>So high our Dragons soar'd into the aire,</l>
                  <l>That looking downe the earth appear'd to me,</l>
                  <l>No bigger then my hand in quantity.</l>
                  <l>There did we view the Kingdomes of the world,</l>
                  <l>And what might please mine eye, I there beheld.</l>
                  <l>Then in this shew let me an Actor be,</l>
                  <l>That this proud Pope may <hi>Faustus</hi> comming see.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let it be so my <hi>Faustus,</hi> but first stay,</l>
                  <l>And view their triumphs, as they passe this way.</l>
                  <l>And then deuise what best contents thy minde,</l>
                  <l>By comming in thine Art to crosse the Pope,</l>
                  <l>Or dash the pride of this solemnity;</l>
                  <l>To make his Monkes and Abbots stand like Apes,</l>
                  <l>And point like Antiques at his triple Crowne:</l>
                  <l>To beate the beades about the Friers Pates,</l>
                  <l>Or clap huge hornes, vpon the Cardinals heads:</l>
                  <l>Or any villany thou canst deuise,</l>
                  <l>And I'le performe it <hi>Faustus:</hi> heark they come:</l>
                  <l>This day shall make thee be admir'd in <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter the Cardinals and Bishops, some bearing Crosiers, some the Pillars, Monkes and Friers, singing their Procession: Then the Pope, and Raymond King of Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with Bruno led in chaines.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <p>Cast downe our Foot-stoole.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ray.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Saxon <hi>Bruno</hi> stoope,</l>
                  <l>Whilst on thy backe his hollinesse ascends</l>
                  <l>Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire and State Pontificall.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that State belongs to me:</l>
                  <l>But thus I fall to <hi>Peter,</hi> not to thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:15"/>
               <speaker>Pope</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tome and <hi>Peter,</hi> shalt thou groueling lie,</l>
                  <l>And crouch before the Papall dignity:</l>
                  <l>Sound Trumpets then, for thus Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Heire,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Bruno's</hi> backe, ascends Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire.</l>
                  <stage>A Flourish while he ascends.</stage>
                  <l>Thus, as the Gods, creepe on with féete of woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>Long ere with Iron hands they punish men,</l>
                  <l>So shall our sleeping vengeance now arise,</l>
                  <l>And smite with death thy hated enterprise.</l>
                  <l>Lord Cardinals of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Padua,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Go forth-with to our holy Consistory,</l>
                  <l>And read amongst the Statutes Decretall,</l>
                  <l>What by the holy Councell held at <hi>Trent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The sacred Sinod hath decréed for him,</l>
                  <l>That doth assume the Papall gouernment,</l>
                  <l>Without election, and a true consent:</l>
                  <l>Away and bring vs word with spéed.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Card.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>We go my Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Cardinals,</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <p>Lord <hi>Raymond.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go hast thée gentle <hi>Mephostophilis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Follow the Cardinals to the Consistory;</l>
                  <l>And as they turne their superstitious Bookes,</l>
                  <l>Strike them with sloth, and drowsy idlenesse;</l>
                  <l>And make them sleepe so sound, that in their shapes,</l>
                  <l>Thy selfe and I, may parly with this Pope:</l>
                  <l>This proud confronter of the Emperour,</l>
                  <l>And in despite of all his Holinesse</l>
                  <l>Restore this <hi>Bruno</hi> to his liberty,</l>
                  <l>And beare him to the States of <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faustus,</hi> I goe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dispath it soone,</l>
                  <l>The Pope shall curse that <hi>Faustus</hi> came to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exit Faustus and Meph.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruno.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> let me haue some right of Law,</l>
                  <l>I was elected by the Emperour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>We will depose the Emperour for that deed,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd curse the people that submit to him;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>th he and thou shalt stand excommunicate, </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:15"/>
                  <l> And interdict from Churches priuiledge,</l>
                  <l>And all society of holy men:</l>
                  <l>He growes to prowd in his authority,</l>
                  <l>Lifting his loftie head aboue the clouds,</l>
                  <l>And like a Steeple ouer-péeres the Church.</l>
                  <l>But wee'le pul downe his haughty insolence:</l>
                  <l>And as Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> our Progenitour,</l>
                  <l>Trode on the neck of <hi>Germane Fredericke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Adding this golden sentence to our praise;</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Peters</hi> heires should tread on Emperours,</l>
                  <l>And walke vpon the dreadfull Adders backe,</l>
                  <l>Treading the Lyon, and the Dragon downe.</l>
                  <l>And fearelesse spurne the killing Basiliske:</l>
                  <l>So will we quell that haughty Schismatique;</l>
                  <l>And by authority Apostolicall</l>
                  <l>Depose him from his Regall Gouernment.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> swore to Princely <hi>Sigismoud,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For him, and the succéeding Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To hold the Emperours their lawfull Lords.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> did abuse the Churches Rites,</l>
                  <l>And therefore none of his Decrees can stand.</l>
                  <l>Is not all power on earth bestowed on vs?</l>
                  <l>And therefore tho we would we cannot erre.</l>
                  <l>Behold this Siluer Belt whereto is fixt</l>
                  <l>Seuen golden seales fast sealed with seuen seales,</l>
                  <l>In token of our seuen-fold power from heauen,</l>
                  <l>To binde or loose, lock fast, condemne, or iudge,</l>
                  <l>Resigne, or seale, or what so pleaseth vs.</l>
                  <l>Then he and thou, and all the world shall stoope,</l>
                  <l>Or be assured of our dreadfull curse,</l>
                  <l>To light as heauy as the paines of hell.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Faustus and Mephosto. like the Cardinals.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>Now tell me <hi>Faustus,</hi> are we not fitted well?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes <hi>Mephosto.</hi> and two such Cardinals</l>
                  <l>Ne're seru'd a holy Pope, as we shall do.</l>
                  <l>But whilst they sleepe within the Consistory, </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:16"/>
                  <l> Let vs salute his reuerend Father-hood.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ray.</speaker>
               <p>Behold my Lord, the Cardinals are return'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Welcome graue Fathers, answere presently,</l>
                  <l>What haue our holy Councell there decreed,</l>
                  <l>Concerning <hi>Bruno</hi> and the Emperour,</l>
                  <l>In quittance of their late conspiracie</l>
                  <l>Against our State, and Papall dignitie?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Most sacred Patron of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By full consent of all the Synod</l>
                  <l>Of Priests and Prelates, it is thus decréed:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Bruno,</hi> and the Germane Emperour</l>
                  <l>Be held as Lollords, and bold Schismatiques,</l>
                  <l>And proud disturbers of the Churches peace.</l>
                  <l>And if that <hi>Bruno</hi> by his owne assent,</l>
                  <l>Without inforcement of the German Péeres,</l>
                  <l>Did séeke to weare the triple Dyadem,</l>
                  <l>And by your death to clime S. <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire.,</l>
                  <l>The Statutes Decretall haue thus decréed,</l>
                  <l>He shall be streight condemn'd of heresie,</l>
                  <l>And on pile of Fagots burnt to death.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is enough: here, take him to your charge,</l>
                  <l>And beare him streight to <hi>Ponto Angelo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in the strongest Tower inclose him fast,</l>
                  <l>To morrow, sitting in our Consistory,</l>
                  <l>With all our Colledge of graue Cardinals,</l>
                  <l>We will determine of his life or death.</l>
                  <l>Here, take his triple Crowne along with you,</l>
                  <l>And leaue it in the Churches treasury.</l>
                  <l>Make haste againe, my good Lord Cardinalls,</l>
                  <l>And take our blessing Apostolicall.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>So, so, was neuer Diuell thus blest before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Away swéet <hi>Mephosto,</hi> be gone,</l>
                  <l>The Cardinals will be plagu'd for this anon.</l>
                  <stage>Ex. Fa. &amp; Mep.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go presently, and bring a banket forth,</l>
                  <l>That we may solemnize S. <hi>Peters</hi> feast,</l>
                  <l>And with Lord <hi>Raymond,</hi> King of Hungary,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inke to our late and happy victory.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </lg>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:16"/> A Senit while the Banquet is brought in; and then Enter Faustus and Mephastophilis in their owne shapes.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Faustus,</hi> come prepare thy selfe for mirth,</l>
                  <l>The sléepy Cardinals are hard at hand,</l>
                  <l>To censure <hi>Bruno,</hi> that is posted hence,</l>
                  <l>And on a proud pac'd Stéed, as swift as thought,</l>
                  <l>Flies ore the Alpes to fruitfull Germany,</l>
                  <l>There to salute the wofull Emperour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Pope will curse them for their sloth to day.</l>
                  <l>That slept both <hi>Bruno</hi> and his crowne away,</l>
                  <l>But now, that <hi>Faustus</hi> may delight his minde,</l>
                  <l>And by their folly make some merriment,</l>
                  <l>Swéet <hi>Mephasto:</hi> so charme me here,</l>
                  <l>That I may walke inuisible to all,</l>
                  <l>And doe what ere I please, vnséene of any.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus</hi> thou shalt, then knéele downe presently,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whilst on thy head I lay my hand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And charme thee with this Magicke wand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>First weare this girdle, then appeare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inuisible to all are here:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Planets seuen, the gloomy aire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hell and the Furies forked haire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pluto's blew fire, and Hecat's tree,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With Magicke spels so compasse thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That no eye may thy body see.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So <hi>Faustus,</hi> now for all their holinesse,</l>
                  <l>Do what thou wilt, thou shalt not be discern'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thankes <hi>Mephasto:</hi> now Friers take héed,</l>
                  <l>Lest <hi>Faustus</hi> make your shauen crownes to bléed.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faustus</hi> no more: sée where the Cardinals come.</p>
               <stage>Enter Pope and all the Lords. Enter the Cardinals with a Booke.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Welcome Lord Cardinals: come sit downe. </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:17"/>
                  <l> Lord <hi>Raymond,</hi> take your seate, Friers attend,</l>
                  <l>And sée that all things be in readinesse,</l>
                  <l>As best beséemes this solemne festiuall.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Card.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>First, may it please your sacred Holinesse,</l>
                  <l>To view the sentence of the reuerend Synod,</l>
                  <l>Concerning <hi>Bruno</hi> and the Emperour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What needs this question? Did I not tell you,</l>
                  <l>To morrow we would fit i'th Consistory,</l>
                  <l>And there determine of his punishment?</l>
                  <l>You brought vs word euen now, it was decréed,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Bruno</hi> and the cursed Emperour</l>
                  <l>Were by the holy Councell both condemn'd</l>
                  <l>For lothed Lollords, and base Schismatiques:</l>
                  <l>Then wherefore would you haue me view that booke?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Card.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Your Grace mistakes, you gaue vs no such charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ray.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deny it not, we all are witnesses</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Bruno</hi> here was late deliuered you,</l>
                  <l>With his rich triple crowne to be reseru'd,</l>
                  <l>And put into the Churches treasury.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Amb. Card.</speaker>
               <p>By holy <hi>Paul</hi> we saw them not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>By <hi>Peter</hi> you shall dye,</l>
                  <l>Vnlesse you bring them forth immediatly:</l>
                  <l>Hale them to prison, lade their limbes with gyues:</l>
                  <l>False Prelates, for this hatefull treachery,</l>
                  <l>Curst be your soules to hellish misery.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So, they are safe: now <hi>Faustus</hi> to the feast,</l>
                  <l>The Pope had neuer such a frolicke guest.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <p>Lord Archbishop of <hi>Reames,</hi> sit downe with vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bish.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke your Holinesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Fall to, the Diuell choke you an you spare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who's that spoke? Friers looke about,</l>
                  <l>Lord <hi>Raymond</hi> pray fall too, I am beholding</l>
                  <l>To the Bishop of Millaine, for this so rare a present.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How now? who snatch't the meat from me!</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>illaines why speake you not?</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ood Lord Archbishop, heres a most daintie dish,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>t me from a Cardinall in France.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:17"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I'le haue that too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What Lollards do attend our Hollinesse,</l>
                  <l>That we receiue such great indignity? fetch me some wine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I, pray do, for <hi>Faustus</hi> is a dry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <p>Lord <hi>Kaymond,</hi> I drink vnto your grace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I pledge your grace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My wine gone too? ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lubbers look about</l>
                  <l>And find the man that doth this villany,</l>
                  <l>Or by our sanctitude you all shall die.</l>
                  <l>I pray my Lords haue patience at this</l>
                  <l>Troublesome banquet.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bish.</speaker>
               <p>Please it your holinesse, I thinke it be some Ghost crept out of Purgatory, and now is come vnto your holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse for his pardon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It may be so:</l>
                  <l>Go then command our Priests to sing a Dirge,</l>
                  <l>To lay the fury of this same troublesome ghost.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How now? must euery bit be spiced with a Crosse?</l>
                  <l>Nay then take that.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O I am slaine, help me my Lords:</l>
                  <l>O come and help to beare my body hence:</l>
                  <l>Damb'd be this soule for euer, for this deed.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exeunt the Pope and his traine.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Me.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Faustus,</hi> what will you do now? for I can tell you</l>
                  <l>You'le be curst with Bell, Booke, and Candle.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bell, Booke, and Candle; Candle, Booke, and Bell,</l>
                  <l>Forward and backward, to curse <hi>Faustus</hi> to hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter the Friers with Bell, Booke, and Candle, for the Dirge.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Frier.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come brethren, let's about our businesse with good deuotion.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cursed be he that stole his holinesse meate from the Table.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maledicat Dominus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cursed be he that stroke his holinesse a blow the face.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maledicat Dominus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:18"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cursed be he that strucke fryer Sandelo a blow on the pate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maledicat Dom.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cursed be he that disturbeth our holy Dirge.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maledicat Dom.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cursed be he that tooke away his holinesse wine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maledicat Dom.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Beate the Friers, fling fire worke among them, and <hi>Exeunt.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Clowne and Dicke, with a Cup.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra <hi>Robin,</hi> we were best looke that your deuill can answere the stealing of this same cup, for the Vintners boy followes vs at the hard heeles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis no matter, let him come; an he follow vs, I'le so coniure him, as he was neuer coniur'd in his life, I warrant him: let me see the cup.</p>
               <stage>Enter Vintner.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Here 'tis: Yonder he comes: Now <hi>Robin,</hi> now or neuer shew thy cunning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vint.</speaker>
               <p>O, are you here? I am glad I haue found you, you are a couple of fine companions: pray where's the cup you stole from the Tauerne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>How, how? we steale a cup? take heed what you say, we looke not like cup-stealers I can tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vint.</speaker>
               <p>Neuer deny't, for I know you haue it, and I'le search you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>Search me? I and spare not: hold the cup <hi>Dick,</hi> come, come, search me, search me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vint.</speaker>
               <p>Come on firra, let me search you now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>I, I, do, do, hold the cup <hi>Robin,</hi> I feare not your searching; we scorne to steale your cups I can tell you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vint.</speaker>
               <p>Neuer out face me for the matter, for sure the cup is betweene you two.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>Nay there you lie, 'tis beyond vs both.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:18"/>
               <speaker>Vint.</speaker>
               <p>A plague take you, I thought 'twas your knauery to take it away: Come, giue it me againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>I much, when can you tell: <hi>Dick,</hi> make me a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and stand close at my backe, and stir not for thy life, <hi>Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> you shall haue your cup anon, say nothing <hi>Dick: O per se o, demogorgon, Belcher</hi> and <hi>Mephostophilis.</hi>
               </p>
               <stage>Enter Mephostophilis.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You Princely Legions of infernall Rule,</l>
                  <l>How am I vexed by these villaines Charmes?</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Constantinople</hi> haue they brought me now,</l>
                  <l>Onely for pleasure of these damned slaues.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>By Lady sir, you haue had a shroud iourney of it, will it please you to take a shoulder of Mutton to supper, and a Tester in your purse, and go backe againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>I, I pray you heartily sir; for wee cal'd you but in ieast I promise you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>To purge the rashnesse of this cursed deed,</l>
                  <l>First, be thou turned to this vgly shape,</l>
                  <l>For Apish deeds transformed to an Ape.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>O braue, an Ape? I pray sir, let me haue the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him about to shew some trickes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>And so thou shalt: be thou transform'd to a dog, and carry him vpon thy backe; away be gone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
               <p>A dog? that's excellent: let the Maids looke well to their porridge-pots, for I'le into the Kitchin presently: come <hi>Dick,</hi> come.</p>
               <stage>Exeunt the two Clownes.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now with the flames of euer-burning fire,</l>
                  <l>I'le wing my selfe and forth-with flie amaine</l>
                  <l>Vnto my <hi>Faustus</hi> to the great Turkes Court.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Martino, and Frederick at seuerall dores.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ho, Officers, Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Hye to the presence to attend the Emperour,</l>
                  <l>Good <hi>Fredericke</hi> see the roomes be voyded straight,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:19"/>
                  <l> His Maiesty is comming to the Hall;</l>
                  <l>Go backe, and see the State in readinesse.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But where is <hi>Bruno</hi> our elected Pope,</l>
                  <l>That on a furies back came post from <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will not his grace consort the Emperour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O yes, and with him comes the <hi>Germane</hi> Coniurer.</l>
                  <l>The learned <hi>Faustus,</hi> fame of <hi>Wittenberge,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The wonder of the world for Magick Art;</l>
                  <l>And he intends to shew great <hi>Carolus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The race of all his stout progenitors;</l>
                  <l>And bring in presence of his Maiesty,</l>
                  <l>The royall shapes and warlike semblances</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Alexander</hi> and his beauteous Paramour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
               <p>Where is <hi>Benuolio?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fast a sleepe I warrant you,</l>
                  <l>He took his rouse with stopes of Rhennish wine,</l>
                  <l>So kindly yesternight to <hi>Bruno's</hi> health,</l>
                  <l>That all this day the sluggard keepes his bed.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
               <p>Sée, sée his window's ope, we'l call to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>What hoe, <hi>Benuolio.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Benuolio aboue at a window, in his nightcap: buttoning.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <p>What a deuill ayle you two?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Speak softly sir, least the deuil heare you:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Faustus</hi> at the Court is lats arriu'd,</l>
                  <l>And at his heeles a thousand furies waite,</l>
                  <l>To accomplish what soeuer the Doctor please.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <p>What of this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come leaue thy chamber first, and thou shalt see</l>
                  <l>This Coniurer performe such rare exploits,</l>
                  <l>Before the Pope and royall Emperour,</l>
                  <l>As neuer yet was seene in <hi>Germany.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Has not the Pope enough of coniuring yet?</l>
                  <l>He was vpon the deuils backe late enough;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d if he be so fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in loue with him,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:19"/>
                  <l> I would he would post with him to <hi>Rome</hi> againe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>Speake, wilt thou come and sée this sport?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Not I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar</speaker>
               <p>Wilt thou stand in thy Window, and sée it then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>I, and I fall not asléepe i'th meane time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <l>The Emperour is at hand, who comes to sée</l>
               <l>What wonders by blacke spels may compast be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Well, go you attend the Emperour: I am content for this once to thrust my head out at a window: for they say, if a man be drunke ouer night, the Diuell cannot hurt him in the morning: if that bee true, I haue a charme in my head, shall controule him as well as the Coniurer, I warrant you.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>A Senit. Charles the Germane Emperour, Bruno, Saxony, Faustus, Mephostophilis, Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke Martino, and Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wonder of men, renown'd Magitian,</l>
                  <l>Thrice learned <hi>Faustus,</hi> welcome to our Court.</l>
                  <l>This déed of thine, in setting <hi>Bruno</hi> frée</l>
                  <l>From his and our professed enemy,</l>
                  <l>Shall adde more excellence vnto thine Art,</l>
                  <l>Then if by powerfull Necromantick spels,</l>
                  <l>Thou couldst command the worlds obedience:</l>
                  <l>For euer be belou'd of <hi>Carolus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And if this <hi>Bruno</hi> thou hast late redéem'd,</l>
                  <l>In peace possesse the triple Diadem,</l>
                  <l>And sit in <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire, despite of chance,</l>
                  <l>Thou shalt be famous through all <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And honour'd of the Germane Emperour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>These gracious words, most royall <hi>Carolus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall make poore <hi>Faustus</hi> to his vtmost power,</l>
                  <l>Both loue and serue the Germane Emperour,</l>
                  <l>And lay his life at holy <hi>Bruno's</hi> feet.</l>
                  <l>For proofe whereof, if so your Grace be pleas'd,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:20"/>
                  <l> The Doctor stands prepar'd, by power of Art,</l>
                  <l>To cast his Magicke charmes, that shall pierce through</l>
                  <l>The Ebon gates of euer-burning hell,</l>
                  <l>And hale the stubborne Furies from their caues,</l>
                  <l>To compasse whatsoere your grace commands.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Bloud he speakes terribly: but for all that, I doe not greatly beléeue him, he lookes as like Coniurer as the Pope to a Coster-monger.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then <hi>Faustus</hi> as thou late didst promise vs,</l>
                  <l>We would behold that famous Conquerour,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Alexander,</hi> and his Paramour,</l>
                  <l>In their true shapes, and state Maiesticall,</l>
                  <l>That we may wonder at their excellence.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your Maiesty shall see them presently,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mephosto</hi> away.</l>
                  <l>And with a solemne noyse of trumpets sound,</l>
                  <l>Present before this royall Emperour,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Alexander</hi> and his beauteous Paramour.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faustus</hi> I will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Well M. Doctor, an your Diuels come not away quickly, you shall haue me asléepe presently: zounds I could eate my selfe for anger, to thinke I haue beene such an Asse all this while, to stand gaping after the diuels Gouernor, and can sée nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Il'e make you feele something anon, if my Art faile me not.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Lord, I must forewarne your Maiesty,</l>
                  <l>That when my Spirits present the royall shapes</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Alexander</hi> and his Paramour,</l>
                  <l>Your grace demand no questions of the King,</l>
                  <l>But in dumbe silence let them come and goe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <p>Be it as <hi>Faustus</hi> please, we are content.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>I, I, and I am content too: and thou bring <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> and his Paramour before the Emperour, Il'e be <hi>Acte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and turne my selfe to a Stagge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>And Il'e play <hi>Diana,</hi> and send you the hornes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ly. </p>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:20"/> Senit. Enter at one the Emperour Alexander, at the other Darius; they meete, Darius is throwne downe, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der kils him; takes off his Crowne, and offering to goe out, his Paramour meetes him, he embraceth her, and sets Darius Crowne vpon her head; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mig backe, both salute the Emperour, who leauing his State, offers to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them, which Faustus seeing, suddenly staies him. Then trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets cease, and Musicke sounds.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>My gracious Lord, you doe forget your selfe,</l>
                  <l>These are but shadowes, not substantiall.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O pardon me, my thoughts are so rauished</l>
                  <l>With fight of this renowned Emperour,</l>
                  <l>That in mine armes I would haue compast him.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Faustus,</hi> since I may not speake to them,</l>
                  <l>To satisfie my longing thoughts at full,</l>
                  <l>Let me this tell thee: I haue heard it said,</l>
                  <l>That this faire Lady, whilest she liu'd on earth,</l>
                  <l>Had on her necke a little wart, or mole;</l>
                  <l>How may I proue that saying to be true▪</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Your Maiesty may boldly goe and see.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus</hi> I see it plaine,</l>
                  <l>And in this sight thou better pleasest me,</l>
                  <l>Then if I gain'd another Monarchie.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Away, be gone.</p>
               <stage>Exit Show.</stage>
               <p>Sée, sée, my gracious Lord, what strange beast is you, that thrusts his head out at window.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O wondrous sight: sée Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Two spreading hornes most strangely fastened</l>
                  <l>Vpon the head of yong <hi>Benvolio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sax.</speaker>
               <p>What is he asléepe, or dead?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>He sléeps my Lord, but dreames not of his hornes,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <p>This sport is excellent: wée'l call and wake him. What ho, <hi>Benvolio.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:21"/>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>A plague vpon you, let me sleepe a while.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <p>I blame thee not to sleepe much, hauing such a hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of thine owne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sax.</speaker>
               <p>Looke vp <hi>Benvolio,</hi> tis the Emperour calls.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>The Emperour? where? O zounds my head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, and thy hornes hold, tis no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er for thy head, for that's arm'd sufficiently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Why how now sir Knight, what hang'd by the hornes? this most horrible: fie, fie, pull in your head for shame, let not all the world wonder at you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Zounds Doctor, is this your villany?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O say not so fir: the Doctor has no skill,</l>
                  <l>No Art, no cunning, to present these Lords,</l>
                  <l>Or bring before this royall Emperour</l>
                  <l>The mightie Monarch, warlicke <hi>Alexander.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If <hi>Faustus</hi> do it, you are streight resolu'd,</l>
                  <l>In bold <hi>Acteons</hi> shape to turne a Stagge.</l>
                  <l>And therefore my Lord, so please your Maiesty,</l>
                  <l>Il'e raise a kennelll of Hounds shall hunt him so,</l>
                  <l>As all his footmanship shall scarce preuaile,</l>
                  <l>To keepe his Carkasse from their bloudy phangs.</l>
                  <l>Ho, <hi>Belimote, Argiron, Asterote.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Hold, hold: zounds hée'l raise vp a kennell of Diuels I thinke anon: good my Lord intreate for me: 'sbloud I am neuer able to endure these torments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then good M. Doctor,</l>
                  <l>Let me intreate you to remoue his hornes,</l>
                  <l>He has done penance now sufficiently.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>My gracious Lord, not so much for iniury done to me, as to delight your Maiesty with some mirth: hath <hi>Faustus</hi> iustly requited this iniurious knight, which being all I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, I am content to remoue his hornes. <hi>Mephastophilis,</hi> transforme him; and hereafter sir, looke you speake well of Schollers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Speake well of yee? 'sbloud and Schollers be such Cuckold-makers to clap hornes of honest mens heades o'this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er, Il'e nere trust smooth faces, and small ruffes more. But
<pb facs="tcp:21791:21"/> an I be not reueng'd for this, would I might be turn'd to a gaping Oyster, and drinke nothing but salt water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Emp.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come <hi>Faustus</hi> while the Emperour liues,</l>
                  <l>In recompence of this thy high desert,</l>
                  <l>Thou shalt command the state of <hi>Germany,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And liue belou'd of mightie <hi>Carolus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Benvolio, Martino, Fredericke, and Souldiers.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay swéet <hi>Benvolio,</hi> let vs sway thy thoughts</l>
                  <l>From this attempt against the Coniurer.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Away, you loue me not, to vrge me thus,</l>
                  <l>Shall I let slip so great an iniury,</l>
                  <l>When euery seruile groome ieasts at my wrongs,</l>
                  <l>And in their rusticke gambals proudly say,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Benvolio</hi>'s head was grac't with hornes to day?</l>
                  <l>O may these eye-lids neuer close againe,</l>
                  <l>Till with my sword I haue that Coniurer slaine.</l>
                  <l>If you will aid me in this enterprise,</l>
                  <l>Then draw your weapons, and be resolute:</l>
                  <l>If not, depart: here will <hi>Benvolio</hi> die,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Faustus</hi> death shall quit my infamie.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, we will stay with thee, betide what may,</l>
                  <l>And kill that Doctor if he come this way.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then gentle <hi>Fredericke</hi> hie thée to the groue,</l>
                  <l>And place our seruants, and our followers</l>
                  <l>close in an ambush there behinde the trées,</l>
                  <l>By this (I know) the Coniurer is neere,</l>
                  <l>I saw him kneele, and kisse the Emperours hand,</l>
                  <l>And take his leaue, laden with rich rewards.</l>
                  <l>Then Souldiers boldly fight; if <hi>Faustus</hi> die,</l>
                  <l>Take you the wealth, leaue vs the victorie.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come souldiers, follow me vnto the groue,</l>
                  <l>Who kils him shall haue gold, and endlesse loue.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit Frederick with the Souldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My head is lighter then it was by th'hornes,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:22"/>
                  <l> But yet my heart more ponderous then my head,</l>
                  <l>And pants vntill I sée that Coniurer dead.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Where shall we place our selues <hi>Benvolio?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here will we stay to bide the first assault,</l>
                  <l>O were that damned Hell-hound but in place,</l>
                  <l>Thou soone shouldst sée me quit my foule disgrace.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Fredericke.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Close, close, the Coniurer is at hand,</l>
                  <l>And all alone, comes walking in his gown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</l>
                  <l>Be ready then, and strike the Peasant downe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mine be that honour then: now sword strike home,</l>
                  <l>For hornes he gaue, Il'e haue his head anone.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Faustus with the false head.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Sée, sée, he comes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No words: this blow ends all,</l>
                  <l>Hell take his soule, his body thus must fall.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Oh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>Grone you Master Doctor?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Breake may his heart with grones: déere <hi>Frederik</hi> sée Thus will I end his griefes immediatly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Strike with a willing hand, his head is off.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>The Diuel's dead, the Furies now may laugh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Was this that sterne aspect, that awfull frowne,</l>
                  <l>Made the grim monarch of infernall spirits,</l>
                  <l>Tremble and quake at his commanding charmes?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>Was this that damned head; whose heart conspir'd <hi>Benvolio's</hi> shame before the Emperour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, that's the head, and here the body lies,</l>
                  <l>Iustly rewarded for his villanies.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come, let's deuise how we may adde more shame</l>
                  <l>To the blacke scandall of his hated name.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>First, on his head, in quittance of my wrongs,</l>
                  <l>Il'e naile huge forked hornes, and let them hang</l>
                  <l>Within the window where he yoak'd me first,</l>
                  <l>That all the world may sée my iust reuenge.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>What vse shall we put his beard to?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:22"/>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Wée'l sell it to a Chimny-swéeper: it will weare out ten birchin broomes I warrant you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>What shall eyes doe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Wee'l put out his eyes, and they shall serue for but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons to his lips, to keepe his tongue from catching cold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <p>An excellent policie: and now sirs, hauing diuided him, what shall the body doe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Zounds the Diuel's aliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> agen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>Giue him his head for Gods sake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay keepe it: <hi>Faustus</hi> will haue heads and hands,</l>
                  <l>I call your hearts to recompence this deed.</l>
                  <l>Knew you not Traytors, I was limitted</l>
                  <l>For foure and twenty yeares, to breathe on earth?</l>
                  <l>And had you cut my body with your swords,</l>
                  <l>Or hew'd this flesh and bones as small as sand,</l>
                  <l>Yet in a minute had my spirit return'd,</l>
                  <l>And I had breath'd a man made frée from harme.</l>
                  <l>But wherefore doe I dally my reuenge?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Asteroth, Belimoth, Mephostophilis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Go horse these traytors on your fiery backes,</l>
                  <l>And mount aloft with them as high as heauen,</l>
                  <l>Thence pitch them headlong to the lowest hell:</l>
                  <l>Yet stay, the world shall see their miserie,</l>
                  <l>And hell shall after plague their treacherie.</l>
                  <l>Go <hi>Belimothe,</hi> and take this caitife hence,</l>
                  <l>And hurle him in some lake of mud and durt:</l>
                  <l>Take thou this other, dragge him through the woods,</l>
                  <l>Amongst the pricking thornes, and sharpest brie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</l>
                  <l>Whilst with my gentle <hi>Mephostophilis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This Traytor flies vnto some stéepie rocke,</l>
                  <l>That rowling downe, may breake the villaines bones,</l>
                  <l>As he intended to dismember me.</l>
                  <l>Fly hence, dispatch my charge immediatly.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ent. Meph. &amp; other Diuels.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>Pitie vs gentle <hi>Faustus,</hi> saue our liues,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>He must needs goe that the Diuell driues.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Spirits with the knights.</stage>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:23"/> Enter the ambusht Souldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Sold.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come sirs, prepare your selues in readinesse,</l>
                  <l>Make hast to help these noble Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>I heard them parly with the Coniurer.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Sold.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>See where he comes, dispatch, and kill the slaue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What's here? an ambush to betray my life:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Faustus</hi> try thy skill: base pesants stand,</l>
                  <l>For loe these Trées remoue at my command,</l>
                  <l>And stand as Bulwarkes twixt your selues and me,</l>
                  <l>To sheild me from your hated treachery:</l>
                  <l>Yet to encounter this your weake attempt,</l>
                  <l>Behold an Army comes incontinent.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Faustus <hi>strikes the dore, and enter a deuill playing on a Drum, after him another bearing an Ensigne: and diuers with weapons, Mephostophilis with fire-workes; they set vpon the Souldiers and driue them out.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Enter at seuerall dores, Benuolio, Fredericke, and Martino, their heads and faces bloudy, and besmear'd with mud and durt; all hauing hornes on their heads.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>What ho, <hi>Benuolio.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <p>Here, what <hi>Frederick,</hi> ho.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>O help me gentle friend; where is <hi>Martino?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deere <hi>Frederick</hi> here,</l>
                  <l>Halfe smother'd in a Lake of mud and durt,</l>
                  <l>Through which the Furies drag'd me by the heeles.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Martino</hi> see,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Benuolio's</hi> hornes againe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>O misery, how now <hi>Benuolio?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <p>Defend me heauen, shall I be haunted still?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>Nay feare not man we haue no power to kill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My friends transformed thus: O hellish spite,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:23"/>
                  <l> Your heads are all set with hornes.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>You hit it right,</l>
                  <l>It is your owne you meane feele on your head.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu▪</speaker>
               <p>'Zons, hornes againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>Nay chafe not man, we all are sped.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What deuill attends this damn'd Magician,</l>
                  <l>That spite of spite, our wrongs are doubled?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
               <p>What may we do, that we may hide our shames?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If we should follow him to worke reuenge,</l>
                  <l>He'd ioyne long Asses eares to these huge hornes,</l>
                  <l>And make vs laughing stockes to all the world.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
               <p>What shall we then do deere <hi>Benuolio?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Benu.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I haue a Castle ioyning neere these woods,</l>
                  <l>And thither wee'le repaire and liue obscure,</l>
                  <l>Till time shall alter this our brutish shapes:</l>
                  <l>Sith blacke disgrace hath thus eclipst our fame.</l>
                  <l>We'le rather die with griefe, then liue with shame.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Faustus, and the Horse-courser, and Mephostophilis.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>I beseech your Worship accept of these forty Dollors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Friend, thou canst not buy so good a horse, for so small a price: I haue no great néed to sell him, but if thou likest him for ten Dollors more, take him, because I see thou hast a good minde to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>I beseech you sir accept of this; I am a very poore man, and haue lost very much of late by horse flesh, and this bargaine will set me vp againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I will not stand with thee, giue me the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: now sirra I must tell you, that you may ride him o're hedge and ditch, and spare him not; but do you heare? in any case, ride him not into the water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>How sir, not into the water? why will he not drink of all waters?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:24"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, he will drinke of all waters, but ride him not into the water; o're hedge and ditch, or where thou wilt, but not into the water: Go bid the Hostler deliuer him vnto you, and remember what I say.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>I warrant you sir; O ioyfull day: Now am I a made man for euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What art thou <hi>Faustus</hi> but a man condemn'd to die?</l>
                  <l>Thy fatall time drawes to a finall end;</l>
                  <l>Despaire doth driue distrust into my thoughts.</l>
                  <l>Confound these passions with a quiet sseepe:</l>
                  <l>Tush Christ did call the Theefe vpon the Crosse,</l>
                  <l>Then rest thee <hi>Faustus</hi> quiet in conceit.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>He sits to sleepe.</stage>
               <stage>Enter the Horse-courser wet.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>O what a cosening Doctor was this? I riding my horse into the water, thinking some hidden mystery had béene in the horse, I had nothing vnder me but a little straw, and had much ado to escape drowning: Well I'le go rouse him, and make him giue me my forty Dollors againe. Ho sirra Doctor, you cosoning scab; Maister Doctor awake, and rise, and giue me my mony againe, for your horse is turned to a bottle of Hay,—Maister Doctor. Alas I am vndone, what shall I do? I haue puld off his leg.</p>
               <stage>He puls off his leg.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>O help, help, the villaine hath murder'd me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>Murder or not murder, now he has but one leg, I'le out-run him, and cast this leg into some ditch or other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Stop him, stop him, stop him—ha, ha, ha, <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus</hi> hath his leg againe, and the Horse-courser a bundle of hay for his forty Dollors.</p>
               <stage>Enter Wagner.</stage>
               <p>How now <hi>Wagner</hi> what newes with thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>If it please you, the Duke of <hi>Vanholt</hi> doth earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreate your company, and hath sent some of his men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttend you with prouision fit for your iourney.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:24"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Vanholt's</hi> an honourable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and one to whom I must be no niggard of my cunning Come away.</p>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Clowne, Dick, Horse-courser, and a Carter.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Come my Maisters, I'le bring you to the best beere in Europe, what ho, Hostis; where be these Whores?</p>
               <stage>Enter Hostis.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Host.</speaker>
               <p>How now, what lacke you? What my old Guesse welcome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra <hi>Dick,</hi> dost thou know why I stand so mute?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>No <hi>Robin,</hi> why is't?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>I am eightéene pence on the score, but say nothing, see if she haue forgotten me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Host.</speaker>
               <p>Who's this, that stands so solemnly by himselfe: what my old Guest?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
               <p>O Hostisse how do you? I hope my score stands still.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Host.</speaker>
               <p>I there's no doubt of that, for me thinkes you make no hast to wipe it out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Why Hostesse, I say, fetch vs some Béere.</p>
               <stage>(Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Host.</speaker>
               <p>You shall presently: looke vp into th'hall thereho.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Come sirs, what shall we do now till mine Hostesse comes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Marry sir, I'le tell you the brauest tale how a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurer seru'd me; you know Doctor <hi>Fauster.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>I, a plague take him, heere's some on's haue cause to know him; did he coniure thee too?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>I'le tell you how he seru'd me: As I was going to <hi>Wittenberge</hi> t'other day, with a loade of Hay, he met me, and asked me what he should giue me for as much Hay as he could eate; now sir, I thinking that a little would serue his turne, bad him take as much as he would for three-farthings; so he presently gaue me my mony, and fell to eating; and as I am a cursen man, he neuer left eating, till he had eate vp all my loade of hay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All.</speaker>
               <p>O monstrous, eate a whole load of Hay!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:25"/>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, yes, that may be; for I haue heard of one, that ha's eate a load of logges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>Now sirs, you shall heare how villanously he seru'd mee: I went to him yesterday to buy a horse of him, and he would by no meanes sell him vnder 40 Dollors; so sir, because I knew him to be such a horse, as would run ouer hedge and ditch, and neuer tyre, I gaue him his money; so when I had my horse, Doctor <hi>Fauster</hi> bad me ride him night and day, and spare him no time; but, quoth he, in any case ride him not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water. Now sir, I thinking the horse had had some quality that he would not haue me know of, what did I but rid him into a great riuer, and when I came iust in the midst my horse vanisht away, and I sate straddling vpon a bottle of Hay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All.</speaker>
               <p>O braue Doctor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horse.</speaker>
               <p>But you shall heare how brauely I seru'd him for it; I went me home to his house, and there I found him asleepe; I kept a hallowing and whooping in his eares, but all could not wake him: I seeing that, tooke him by the leg, and neuer rested pulling, till I had pul'd me his leg quit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> off, and now 'tis at home in mine Hostry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>And has the Doctor but one leg then? that's excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, for one of his deuils turn'd me, into the likenesse of an Apes face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Some more drinke Hostesse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Hearke you, we'le into another roome and drinke a while, and then we'le go seeke out the Doctor.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
            <stage>Enter the Duke of Vanholt; his Dutches, Faustus, and Mephostophilis.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <p>Thankes Maister Doctor, for these pleasant sights, Nor know I how sufficiently to recompence your great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts in erecting that inchanted Castle in the Aire: the Sight whereof so delighted me,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </speaker>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>thing in the world could please me more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:25"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I do thinke my selfe my good Lord, highly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced, in that it pleaseth your grace to thinke but well of that which <hi>Faustus</hi> hath performed. But gratious Lady, it may be▪ that you haue taken no pleasure in those sights; there for I pray you tell me, what is the thing you most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to haue, be it in the world, it shall be yours: I haue heard that great bellyed women, do long for things, are rare and dainty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
               <p>True Maister Doctor, and since I finde you so kind I will make knowne vnto you what my heart desires to haue, and were it now Summer, as it is Ianuary, a dead time of the Winter, I would request no better meate, then a dish of ripe grapes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fau.</speaker>
               <p>This is but a small matter: Go <hi>Mephostophilis,</hi> away.</p>
               <stage>Exit Mephosto.</stage>
               <p>Madam, I will do more then this for your content.</p>
               <stage>Enter Mepho. agen with the grapes.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here, now taste yee these, they should be good</l>
                  <l>For they come from a farre Country I can tell you.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <p>This makes me wonder more then all the rest, that at this time of the yeare, when euery Tree is barren of his fruite, from whence you had these ripe grapes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Please it your grace, the yeare is diuided into two circles ouer the whole world, so that when it is Winter with vs, in the contrary circle it is likewise Summer with them, as in <hi>India, Saba,</hi> and such Countries that lye farre East, where they haue fruit twice a yeare. From whence, by meanes of a swift spirit that I haue, I had these grapes brought as you see.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lady</hi> And trust me, they are the sweetest grapes that e're I tasted.</p>
               <stage>The Clowne bounce at the gate, within.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>What rude disturbers haue we at the gate?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:26"/>
                  <l> Go pacifie their fury set it ope,</l>
                  <l>And then demand of them, what they would haue.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>They knocke againe, and call out to talke with Faustus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A Seruant.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why how now Maisters, what a coyle is there?</l>
                  <l>What is the reason you disturbe the Duke?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>We haue no reason for it, therefore a fig for him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>Why saucy varlets, dare you be so bold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horsc.</speaker>
               <p>I hope sir, we haue wit enough to be more bold then welcome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>It appeares so, pray be bold else-where,</l>
                  <l>And trouble not the Duke.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <p>What would they haue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>They all cry out to speake with Doctor <hi>Faustus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>I, and we will speake with him,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <p>Will you sir? Commit the Rascals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Commit with vs, he were as good commit with his father, as commit with vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I do beseech your grace let them come in,</l>
                  <l>They are good subiect for a merriment.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <p>Do as thou wilt <hi>Faustus,</hi> I giue thee leaue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke your grace:</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the Clowne, Dick, Carter, and Horse-courser.</stage>
            <lg>
               <l>Why, how now my goods friends?</l>
               <l>'Faith you are too outragious, but come neere,</l>
               <l>I haue procur'd your pardons: welcome all.</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Nay sir, we will be wellcome for our mony, and we will pay for what we take: What ho, giue's halfe a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen of Beere here, and be hang'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fanst.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, hearke you, can you tell me where you are?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>I marry can I, we are vnder heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>I but sir sauce box, know you in what place?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:26"/>
               <speaker>Horsc.</speaker>
               <p>I, I, the house is good enough to drink in: Zons fill vs some Beere, or we'll breake all the barrels in the hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se, and dash out all your braines with your Bottles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be not so furious: come you shall haue Beere.</l>
                  <l>My Lord, beseech you giue me leaue a while,</l>
                  <l>I'le gage my credit, 'twill content your grace.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>With all my heart kind Doctor, please thy selfe,</l>
                  <l>Our seruants, and our Courts at thy command.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I humbly thanke your grace: then fetch some Beere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horsc.</speaker>
               <p>I mary, there spake a Doctor indeed, and 'faith Ile drinke a health to thy woodden leg for that word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>My woodden leg? what dost thou meane by that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Ha, ha, ha, dost heare him <hi>Dick,</hi> he has forgot his legge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horsc.</speaker>
               <p>I, I. he does not stand much vpon that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>No faith, not much vpon a woodden leg.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Good Lord, that flesh and bloud should be so fraile with your Worship: Do not you remember a Horse-courser you sold a horse to?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I remember I sold one a horse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>And do you remember you bid he should not ride into the water?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I do verie well remember that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>And do you remember nothing of your leg?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>No in good sooth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Then I pray remember your curtesie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I thank you sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Car.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis not so much worth; I pray you tel me one thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>What's that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Be both your legs bedfellowes euery night together?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Wouldst thou make a <hi>Colossus</hi> of me, that thou as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest me such questions?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>No truelie sir, I would make nothing of you, but I would faine know that.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Hostesse with drinke.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Then I assure thee certainelie they are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:27"/>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you, I am fully satisfied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>But wherefore dost thou aske{reversed ?}</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>For nothing sir: but me thinkes you should haue a wooden bedfellow of one of'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horsc.</speaker>
               <p>Why do you heare sir, did not I pull off one of your legs when you were asleepe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>But I haue it againe now I am awake: looke you heere sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All.</speaker>
               <p>O horrible, had the Doctor three legs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
               <p>Do you remember sir, how you cosened me and eat vp my load of—</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Faustus charmes him dumb.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dick.</speaker>
               <p>Do you remember how you made me weare an Apes—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Horsc.</speaker>
               <p>You whoreson coniuring scab, do you remember how yo cosened me with a ho—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clow.</speaker>
               <p>Ha'you forgotten me? you thinke to carry it away with your <hi>Hey-passe,</hi> and <hi>Re-passe:</hi> do you remember the dogs fa—</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Clownes.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Host.</speaker>
               <p>Who payes for the Ale? heare you Maister Doctor, now you haue sent away my guesse, I pray who shall pay me for my A—?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit Hostesse.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Lord,</l>
                  <l>We are much beholding to this learned man.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>So are we Madam, which we will recompence</l>
                  <l>With all the loue and kindnesse that we may.</l>
                  <l>His Artfull sport, driues all sad thoughts away.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Thunder and lightning: Enter deuils with couer'd dishes: Mephostophilis leades them into Faustus Study: Then enter Wagner.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <p>I think my Maister means to die shortly, he has made his will, &amp; giuen me his wealth, his house, his goods, &amp; store of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:27"/> golden plate; besides two thousand duckets ready coin'd: I wonder what he meanes, if death were nie, he would not fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick thus: hée's now at supper with the schollers, where ther'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> such belly-chéere, as <hi>Wagner</hi> in his life nere saw the like: and sée where they come, belike the feast is done.</p>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Faustus, Mephostophilis, and two or three Schollers.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Schol.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>M. Doctor <hi>Faustus,</hi> since our conference about faire Ladies, which was the beautifullest in all the world, we haue determin'd with our selues, that <hi>Hellen</hi> of Gréece was the admirablest Lady that euer liu'd: therefore M. Doctor, if you will doe vs so much fauour, as to let vs sée that péerelesse dame of Gréece, whom all the world admires for Maiesty, we should thinke our selues much beholding vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gentlemen, for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> I know your friendship is vnfain'd,</l>
                  <l>It is not <hi>Faustus</hi> custome to deny</l>
                  <l>The iust request of those that wish him well:</l>
                  <l>You shall behold that péerelesse dame of Gréece,</l>
                  <l>No otherwise for pompe or Maiesty,</l>
                  <l>Then when sir <hi>Paris</hi> crost the seas with her,</l>
                  <l>And brought the spoyles to rich <hi>Dardania:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be silent then, for danger is in words.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Musicke sound, Mephosto brings in Hellen, she passeth ouer the stage.</stage>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Was this faire <hi>Hellen,</hi> whose admired worth</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Greece</hi> with ten yeares warres afflict poore <hi>Troy?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>Too simple is my wit to tell her worth,</l>
                  <l>Whom all the world admires for maiesty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>Now we haue seene the pride of Natures worke,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l take our leaues, and for this blessed sight</l>
                  <l>Happy and blest be <hi>Faustus</hi> euermore.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exeunt Schollers.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen farewell: the same wish I to you.</p>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:28"/> Enter an old Man.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old Man.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O gentle <hi>Faustus</hi> leaue this damned Art,</l>
                  <l>This Magicke, that will charme thy soule to hell,</l>
                  <l>And quite bereaue thee of saluation.</l>
                  <l>Though thou hast now offended like a man,</l>
                  <l>Doe not perseuer in it like a Diuell;</l>
                  <l>Yet, yet, thou hast an amiable soule,</l>
                  <l>If sin by custome grow not into nature:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Faustus,</hi> will repentance come too late,</l>
                  <l>Then thou art banisht from the sight of heauen;</l>
                  <l>No mortall can expresse the paines of hell.</l>
                  <l>It may be this my exhortation</l>
                  <l>Séemes harsh, and all vnpleasant; let it not,</l>
                  <l>For gentle sonne, I speake it not in wrath,</l>
                  <l>Or enuy of thée, but in tender loue,</l>
                  <l>And pitty of thy future miserie.</l>
                  <l>And so haue hope, that this my kinde rebuke,</l>
                  <l>Checking thy body, may amend thy soule.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where art thou <hi>Faustus?</hi> wretch, what hast thou done?</l>
                  <l>Hell claimes his right, &amp; with a roaring voyce,</l>
                  <stage>Meph. giues him a dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</stage>
                  <l>Saies <hi>Faustus</hi> come, thine houre is almost come,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Faustus</hi> now will come to do thée right.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O stay good <hi>Faustus,</hi> stay thy desperate steps.</l>
                  <l>I see an Angell houer ore thy head,</l>
                  <l>And with a vyoll full of pretious gracs,</l>
                  <l>Offers to poure the same into thy soule,</l>
                  <l>Then call for mercy, and auoyd despaire.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O friend, I féele thy words to cōfort my distressed soule,</l>
                  <l>Leaue me a while, to ponder on my sinnes.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Old.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus</hi> I leaue thee, but with griefe of heart,</l>
                  <l>Fearing the enemy of thy haplesse soule.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Accursed <hi>Faustus,</hi> wretch what hast thou done?</l>
                  <l>I do repent, and yet I doe despaire,</l>
                  <l>Hell striues with grace for conquest in my breast:</l>
                  <l>What shall I doe to shun the snares of death?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou traytor <hi>Faustus,</hi> I arrest thy soule,</l>
                  <l>For disobedience to my soueraigne Lord,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:28"/>
                  <l> Reuolt, or I'le in peece-meale teare thy flesh.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I do repent I ere offended him,</l>
                  <l>Sweet <hi>Mephasto:</hi> intreat thy Lord</l>
                  <l>To pardon my vniust presumption,</l>
                  <l>And with my bloud againe I will confirme</l>
                  <l>The former vow I made to <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do it then <hi>Faustus,</hi> with vnfained heart,</l>
                  <l>Lest greater dangers do attend thy drift.</l>
                  <l>Torment sweet friend, that base and aged man,</l>
                  <l>That durst disswade me from thy <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With greatest torment that our hell affoords.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>His faith is great, I cannot touch his soule;</l>
                  <l>But what I may afflict his body with,</l>
                  <l>I will attempt, which is but little worth.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>One thing good seruant let me craue of thee,</l>
                  <l>To glut the longing of my hearts desire,</l>
                  <l>That I may haue vnto my paramour,</l>
                  <l>That heauenly <hi>Hellen,</hi> which I saw of late,</l>
                  <l>Whose sweet embraces may extinguish cleare,</l>
                  <l>Those thoughts that do disswade me from my vow,</l>
                  <l>And keepe my vow I made to <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, or what else my <hi>Faustus</hi> shall desire,</l>
                  <l>Shall be perform'd in twinkling of an eye.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Hellen againe, passing ouer betweene two Cupids.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Was this the face that Launcht a thousand ships,</l>
                  <l>And burnt the toplesse Towers of <hi>Ilium?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sweet <hi>Hellen</hi> make me immortall with a kisse:</l>
                  <l>Her lips sucke forth my soule, see where it flies.</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Hellen,</hi> come, giue me my soule againe,</l>
                  <l>Here will I dwell, for heauen is in these lippes,</l>
                  <l>And all is drosse that is not <hi>Helena.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will be <hi>Paris,</hi> and for loue of thee,</l>
                  <l>In stead of <hi>Troy</hi> shall <hi>Wittenberg</hi> be sack't,</l>
                  <l>And I will combat with weake <hi>Menelaus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And weare thy colours on my plumed crest.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:29"/>
                  <l> Yea, I will wound <hi>Achilles</hi> in the heele,</l>
                  <l>And then returne to <hi>Hellen</hi> for a kisse.</l>
                  <l>O thou art fairer then the euenings aire,</l>
                  <l>Clad in the beauty of a thousand starres:</l>
                  <l>Brighter art thou then flaming <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When he appear'd to haplesse <hi>Sem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More louely then the Monarch of the sky,</l>
                  <l>In wanton <hi>Arethusa's</hi> azure armes,</l>
                  <l>And none but thou shalt be my Paramour.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Thunder. Enter Lucifer, Belzebub, and Mephostophilis.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lucif.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus from infernall <hi>Dis</hi> do we ascend</l>
                  <l>To view the subiects of our Monarchy,</l>
                  <l>Those soules which sinne, seales the blacke sonnes of hell,</l>
                  <l>'Mong which as chiefe, <hi>Faustus</hi> we come to thee,</l>
                  <l>Bringing with vs lasting damnation,</l>
                  <l>To wait vpon thy soule; the time is come</l>
                  <l>Which makes it forfeit.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And this gloomy night,</l>
                  <l>Here in this roome will wretched <hi>Faustus</hi> be.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bels.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And here wee'l stay,</l>
                  <l>To marke him how he doth demeane himselfe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>How should he, but in desperate lunacie.</l>
                  <l>Fond worldling, now his heart bloud dries with griefe;</l>
                  <l>His conscience kils it, and his labouring braine,</l>
                  <l>Begets a world of idle fantasies,</l>
                  <l>To ouer-reach the Diuell; but all in vaine,</l>
                  <l>His store of pleasures must be sauc'd with paine.</l>
                  <l>He and his seruant <hi>Wagner</hi> are at hand,</l>
                  <l>Both come from drawing <hi>Faustus</hi> latest will.</l>
                  <l>See where they come.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Faustus and Wagner.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Say <hi>Wagner,</hi> thou hast perus'd my will,</l>
                  <l>How dost thou like it?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wag.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sir, so wondrous well,</l>
                  <l>As in all humble dutie, I do yeeld</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and lasting seruice for your loue.</l>
                  <stage>Enter the scholers.</stage>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21791:29"/>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Gramercies <hi>Wagner.</hi> Welcome gentlemen.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Now worthy <hi>Faustus:</hi> me thinks your looks are chang'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Oh gentlemen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What ailes <hi>Faustus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah my swéet chamber-fellow, had I liu'd with thee,</l>
                  <l>Then had I liued still, but now must dye eternally.</l>
                  <l>Looke sirs, comes he not, comes he not?</l>
               </lg>
               <p n="1">1. O my déere <hi>Faustus</hi> what imports this feare?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is all our pleasure turn'd to melancholy?</p>
               <p n="3">3. He is not well with being ouer solitarie.</p>
               <p n="2">2 If it be so, wée'l haue Physitians, and <hi>Faustus</hi> shall bee cur'd.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Tis but a surfet sir, feare nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>A surfet of deadly sin, that hath damn'd both body and soule.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Yet <hi>Faustus</hi> looke vp to heauen, and remember mercy is infinite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Faustus</hi> offence can nere be pardoned,</l>
                  <l>The serpent that tempted <hi>Eue</hi> may be saued,</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But not <hi>Faustus.</hi> O gentlemen heare with patience, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not at my spéeches, though my heart pant &amp; quiuer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that I haue béene a student here these 30 yeares. O would I had neuer seene <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> neuer read book, &amp; what wonders I haue done, all <hi>Germany</hi> can witnesse: yea all the world, for which <hi>Faustus</hi> hath lost both <hi>Germany</hi> &amp; the world, yea heauen it selfe: heauen the seate of God, the Throne of the Blessed, the Kingdome of Ioy, and must remaine in hell for euer. Hell, O hell for euer. Sweet friends, what shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of <hi>Faustus</hi> being in hell for euer?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Yet <hi>Faustus</hi> call on God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>On God, whom <hi>Faustus</hi> hath abiur'd? on God, whom <hi>Faustus</hi> hath blasphem'd? O my God, I would wéepe, but the Diuell drawes in my teares. Gush forth bloud in stead of teares, yea life and soule: oh hee stayes my tongue: I would lift vp my hands, but see they hold 'em, they hold 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All.</speaker>
               <p>Who <hi>Faustus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Why <hi>Lucifer</hi> and <hi>Mephostophilis:</hi> O gentlemen,
<pb facs="tcp:21791:30"/> I gaue them my soule for my cunning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All.</speaker>
               <p>O God forbid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>God forbade it indéed, but <hi>Faustus</hi> hath done it: for the vaine pleasure of foure and twenty yeares hath <hi>Faustus</hi> lost eternall ioy and felicitie. I writ them a bill with mine owne bloud, the date is expired: this is the time, and he will fetch mée.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Why did not <hi>Faustus</hi> tell vs of this before, that Diuines might haue prayd for thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Oft haue I thought to haue done so: but the Diuel threatned to teare me in peeces if I nam'd God: to fetch me body and soule, if I once gaue eare to Diuinitie: and now 'ts too late. Gentlemen away, least you perish with me.</p>
               <p n="2">2 O what may we do to saue <hi>Faustus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Talke not of me, but saue your selues and depart.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God will strengthen me, I will stay with <hi>Faustus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Tempt not God sweet friend, but let vs into the next roome, and pray for him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>I, pray for me, pray for me: and what noyse soeuer you heare, come not vnto me, for nothing can rescue me.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Pray thou, and we will pray, that God may haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpon thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen farewell: if I liue till morning, Il'e vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit you: if not, <hi>Faustus</hi> is gone to hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faustus,</hi> farewell.</p>
               <stage>Exeunt Schollers.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I <hi>Faustus,</hi> now thou hast no hope of heauen,</l>
                  <l>Therefore despaire, thinke onely vpon hell;</l>
                  <l>For that must be thy mansion, there to dwell.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou bewitching fiend, 'twas thy temptation,</l>
                  <l>Hath rab'd me of eternall happinesse.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meph.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I doe confesse it <hi>Faustus,</hi> and reioyce;</l>
                  <l>'Twas I, that when thou wer't i' the way to heauen,</l>
                  <l>Damb'd vp thy passage, when thou took'st the booke,</l>
                  <l>To view the Scriptures, then I turn'd the leaues</l>
                  <l>And led thine eye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>p'st thou? 'tis too late, despaire, farewell,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:30"/>
                  <l> Fooles that will laugh on earth, most wéepe in hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
               <stage>Enter the good Angell, and the bad Angell at seuerall doores.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Faustus,</hi> if thou hadst giuen eare to me,</l>
                  <l>Innumerable ioyes had followed thée.</l>
                  <l>But thou didst loue the world.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gaue eare to me,</l>
                  <l>And now must taste hels paines perpetually.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good.</speaker>
               <p>O what will all thy riches, pleasures, pompes, Auaile thée now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nothing but vexe thée more,</l>
                  <l>To want in hell, that had on earth such store.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Musicke while the Throne descends.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Good.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou hast lost celestiall happinesse,</l>
                  <l>Pleasures vnspeakeable, blisse without end.</l>
                  <l>Hadst thou affected swéet diuinitie,</l>
                  <l>Hell, or the Diuell, had had no power on thee.</l>
                  <l>Hadst thou kept on that way, <hi>Faustus</hi> behold,</l>
                  <l>In what resplendant glory thou hadst set</l>
                  <l>In yonder throne, like those bright shining Saints,</l>
                  <l>And triumpht ouer hell, that hast thou lost,</l>
                  <l>And now poore soule must thy good Angell leaue thee,</l>
                  <l>The iawes of hell are open to receiue thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Hell is discouered.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Faustus</hi> let thine eyes with horror stare</l>
                  <l>Into that vaste perpetuall torture-house,</l>
                  <l>There are the Furies tossing damned soules,</l>
                  <l>On burning forkes: their bodies broyle in lead.</l>
                  <l>There are liue quarters broyling on the coles,</l>
                  <l>That ner'e can die: this euer-burning chaire,</l>
                  <l>Is for ore-tortur'd soules to rest them in.</l>
                  <l>These, that are fed with soppes of flaming fire,</l>
                  <l>Were gluttons, and lou'd only delicates,</l>
                  <l>And laught to see the poore starue at their gates:</l>
                  <l>But yet all these are nothing, thou shalt see</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:31"/>
                  <l> ten thousand tortures that more horrid be.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <p>O, I haue seene enough to torture me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bad.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, thou must feele them, taste the smart of all.</l>
                  <l>He that loues pleasure, must for pleasure fall:</l>
                  <l>And so I leaue thee <hi>Faustus</hi> till anon,</l>
                  <l>Then wilt thou tumble in confusion.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>The Clock strikes eleuen.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O <hi>Faustus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now hast thou but one bare houre to liue,</l>
                  <l>And then thou must be damn'd perpetually.</l>
                  <l>Stand still you euer mouing Spheares of heauen,</l>
                  <l>That time may cease, and midnight neuer come.</l>
                  <l>Faire natures eye, rise, rise againe and make</l>
                  <l>Perpetuall day: or let this houre be but a yeare,</l>
                  <l>A month, a weeke, a naturall day,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Faustus</hi> may repent, and saue his soule.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O lente lente currite noctis equi:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Stars moue still, Time runs, the Clocke will strike.</l>
                  <l>The deuill will come, and <hi>Faustus</hi> must be damn'd.</l>
                  <l>O I'le leape vp to heauen: who puls me downe?</l>
                  <l>One drop of bloud will saue me; oh my Christ,</l>
                  <l>Rend not my heart, for naming of my Christ.</l>
                  <l>Yet will I call on him: O spare me <hi>Lucifer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where is it now? 'tis gone.</l>
                  <l>And see a threatning Arme, an angry Brow.</l>
                  <l>Mountaines and Hils, come, come, and fall on me,</l>
                  <l>And hide me from the heauy wrath of heauen.</l>
                  <l>No? Then will I headlong run into the earth:</l>
                  <l>Gape earth; O no, it will not harbour me.</l>
                  <l>You Starres that raign'd at my natiuity,</l>
                  <l>Whose influence hath allotted death and hell;</l>
                  <l>Now draw vp <hi>Faustus</hi> like a foggy mist,</l>
                  <l>Into the entrals of you labouring cloud,</l>
                  <l>That when you vomite forth into the aire,</l>
                  <l>My limbes may issue from your smoky mouthes,</l>
                  <l>But let my soule mount, and ascend to heauen.</l>
                  <stage>The Watch strikes.</stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:31"/>
                  <l> O halfe the houre is past: 'twill all be past anone:</l>
                  <l>O, if my soule must suffer for my sinne,</l>
                  <l>Impose some end to my incessant paine:</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Faustus</hi> liue in hell a thousand yeares,</l>
                  <l>A hundred thousand, and at last be sau'd.</l>
                  <l>No end is limited to damned soules.</l>
                  <l>Why wert thou not a creature wanting soule?</l>
                  <l>Or why is this immortall that thou hast?</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Pythagoras Metemsycosis;</hi> were that true,</l>
                  <l>This soule should flie from me, and I be chang'd</l>
                  <l>Into some brutish beast.</l>
                  <l>All beasts are happy, for when they die,</l>
                  <l>Their soules are soone dissolu'd in elements,</l>
                  <l>But mine must liue still to be plagu'd in hell.</l>
                  <l>Curst be the parents that ingendred me;</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Faustus,</hi> curse thy selfe, curse <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That hath depriu'd thee of the ioies of heauen.</l>
                  <stage>The clocke strikes twelue</stage>
                  <l>It strikes, it strikes; now body turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to aire,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Lucifer</hi> will beare thee quicke to hell.</l>
                  <l>O soule be chang'd into small water drops,</l>
                  <l>and fall into the Ocean ne're be found.</l>
                  <stage>Thunder, and enter the deuils.</stage>
                  <l>O mercy heauen, looke not so fierce on me;</l>
                  <l>Adders and serpents let me breathe a while:</l>
                  <l>Vgly hell gape not; come not <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'le burne my bookes; oh <hi>Mephostophilis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter the Schollers.</stage>
               </lg>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>Come Gentlemen, let vs go visit <hi>Faustus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For such a dreadfull night, was neuer seene,</l>
                  <l>Since first the worlds creation did begin.</l>
                  <l>Such fearefull shrikes, and cries, were neuer heard,</l>
                  <l>Pray heauen the Doctor haue escapt the danger.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>O help vs heauen, see, here are <hi>Faustus</hi> limbs,</l>
                  <l>All torne asunder by the hand of death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21791:32"/>
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>The deuils whom <hi>Faustus</hi> seru'd haue to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> him th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>For twixt the houres of twelue and one, methought</l>
                  <l>I heard him shreeke and call aloud for helps▪</l>
                  <l>At which selfe time the house seem'd all on fire,</l>
                  <l>With dreadfull horror of these damned fiends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Well Gentlemen, tho <hi>Faustus</hi> end be such</l>
                  <l>As euery Christian heart laments to thinke on:</l>
                  <l>Yet for he was a Scholler, once admired</l>
                  <l>For wondrous knowledge in our <hi>Germane</hi> schooles,</l>
                  <l>We'll giue his mangled limbs due buryall:</l>
                  <l>And all the Students clothed in mourning blacke,</l>
                  <l>Shall waite vpon his heauy funerall.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Chorus.</stage>
                  <l>Cut is the branch that might haue growne full straight,</l>
                  <l>And burned is <hi>Apollo's</hi> Lawrell bough,</l>
                  <l>That some time grew within this learned man,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faustus</hi> is gone, regard his hellish fall,</l>
                  <l>Whose fiendfull fortune may exhort the wise</l>
                  <l>Onely to wonder at vnlawfull things:</l>
                  <l>Whose deepnesse doth intice such forward wits,</l>
                  <l>To practise more then heauenly power permits.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Terminat hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diem, Terminat Author opus.</stage>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21791:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>